<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two discourses, the first, a Christian's exhortation, against the fears of death: the second, a brief and clear declaration of the resurrection of the dead With suitable meditations and prayers touching life and death. Recommended as proper to be given at funerals. By W. S.</title>
            <author>W. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 163 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 93 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92747</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S207A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229960</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895749</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895749</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153299</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92747)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153299)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2358:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two discourses, the first, a Christian's exhortation, against the fears of death: the second, a brief and clear declaration of the resurrection of the dead With suitable meditations and prayers touching life and death. Recommended as proper to be given at funerals. By W. S.</title>
                  <author>W. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>179, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Tho. Bever, at the Hand and Star, next to the Middle Temple-Gate, near Temple Bar,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Death --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prayers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:153299:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153299:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153299:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153299:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153299:3"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Chriſtian Exortation againſt the fearc of Death.</head>
                  <q>
                     <p>For ſince by man came death, by man came alſo the reſurrection of the dead.</p> 
                     <bibl>Corin: 15 Ch. p: 21.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153299:3"/>
            <p>TWO DISCOURSES, The FIRST, A CHRISTIAN'S EXHORTATION, Againſt the FEARS OF DEATH: The SECOND, A brief and clear Declaration of the Reſurrection of the Dead.</p>
            <p>With ſuitable Meditations and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers touching LIFE and DEATH.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Recommended as proper to be given at Funerals</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>W. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Bever,</hi> at the <hi>Hand</hi> and <hi>Star,</hi> next to the Middle <hi>Temple-Gate,</hi> near <hi>Temple Bar,</hi> 1690. Price Bound 1 Shilling.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourses">
            <div type="discourse">
               <pb facs="tcp:153299:4"/>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:153299:4"/>
               <head>A DISCOURSE Againſt the Fears of DEATH.</head>
               <p>PLATO ſaid, <hi>That the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy wherein Man (living in this World) ſhould princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally exerciſe himſelf, is the Meditation of Death.</hi> That is to ſay, of his condition in the World, frail, diſeaſed, and mortal; of the divers accidents of this humane Life, and of the Hour of Death, ſo uncertain and unknown; to the end that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153299:5"/>theſe things, he might with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw his affection and truſt from this World, that he might deſpiſe it, and all temporal things, wherein he ſees and diſcovers ſo much inconſtancy, and ſuch ſuddain and frequent mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations or changes: and that by ſuch a deſpiſing of uncertain and caſual things, he ſhould ſtir up himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a contemplation of thoſe that are Divine and Heavenly; and forſaking that which is here periſhing and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory, he ſhould chooſe his part in Heaven, and ſhould ſtay himſelf at that which is permanent and eternal. For the like reaſon <hi>Philip,</hi> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Alexander the Great,</hi> a man of good underſtanding, and of very great conſideration, to the end that in the midſt of his great proſperity, he ſhould not forget himſelf in his Duty, gave order that one of his Gentlemen ſhould every day at his waking, come and ſpeak theſe words unto him; <hi>King, have in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153299:5"/>that thou art a mortal Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Jeſus Chriſt alſo, our Saviour and Maſter, intending the ſame, doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort us to Watch, and to lay up Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in Heaven, and not on Earth, where all things are uncertain and changeable. We ſee by this, that during our Life we cannot do bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then to think upon Death, and our Body being upon the Earth, to accuſtom our ſelves to have always our Spirit and Heart in Heaven. Now becauſe that the remembrance of Death is a fearful thing to many, I have bethought my ſelf to paſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way my Griefs, and to recreate my ſelf from my other Studies; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to give you a teſtimony of the Obligation which I think I have to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, as well for the good which you have done unto me, as for the Friendſhip which you bear me, to write unto you, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent this ſmall Treatiſe, wherein I have briefly touched certain Points,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153299:6"/>wherewith the Faithful may Arm themſelves againſt Death: which he ought to do in time, and prepare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to receive it with aſſurance, at ſuch time as it ſhall pleaſe God to ſend it; for that which doth aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh many, is that the coming there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is ſuddain unto them, and that they are ſurprized unlooked for. We ſee by experience in a frontier Town, that when it is well Victual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and provided of all things neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, to with-ſtand a long Siege, thoſe within are a great deal the more aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured and bold; whereas if it were unprovided, they would ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed and tremble with fear, if they ſhould chance to ſee the approaching of the Siege. It is eaſie to judge by that, of what importance it is to have prevented a danger, and to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for it.</p>
               <p>To provide therefore and arm the Faithful Man againſt Death, we muſt note that there are two ſorts of it:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153299:6"/>the one is <hi>temporal,</hi> of the <hi>body,</hi> which Chriſtians ought to deſire; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is <hi>eternal,</hi> of <hi>body</hi> and <hi>Soul,</hi> which they ought not to fear, perſevering in the Faith of our Lord.</p>
               <p>That it is ſo, all Fear pre-ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth evil and danger; we do not fear that which is good, but long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, deſire and purſue it, and when it offers it ſelf, we receive it joyfully; but an evil we apprehend and fear, we fly from it, and when it happens unto us, we ſorrow and do complain. If then it doth appear by good and evident Proofs, that the Faithful Man is not in danger of this ſecond Death, may we not then conclude, that if we fear it, it is fooliſh and without occaſion? And ſurely if we had judgment, and never ſo little Faith, it were ſufficient preſently to take away the fear of it from us.</p>
               <p>For firſt, the proper nature of <hi>faith</hi> is to animate and quicken our <hi>heart,</hi> ſo ſoon as it is received in us. <hi>The
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153299:7"/>Juſt</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>ſhall live by Faith.</hi> Now even ſo as the Body, whiles the Soul is in it, liveth, and dieth not, until ſuch time as it be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from it; no more doth the Faithful Man, perſevering in the Faith which hath been inſpired and put into his Heart by the Grace of God. Although (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) <hi>I ſhould walk in the midſt of the ſhadow of Death, I will not fear; for Thou art with me O Lord!</hi> What was the cauſe of this aſſurance? was it not Faith? Armed wherewith, we ought no more to fear Death, then we do Sickneſs when we are in perfect <hi>health,</hi> well diſpoſed, and in good liking; or Poverty, when we have plenty and abundance of all good things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> By Faith we have remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and an abolition of all the faults which we have done; Why do we then fear <hi>Death?</hi> There is no Death where there is no Sin; <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Death <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Paul:</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:153299:7"/>and elſewhere; <hi>The Reward of Sin is Death:</hi> Sin cauſeth God to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with us, and that in His Anger He condemneth us to Death. Now all Seeds doth bring forth according to their ſort and quality: The Wheat bringeth forth Wheat, and the Rye, Rye; and we muſt not hope for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Fruit, if there be not Seed before hand.</p>
               <p>This being true, and witneſſed in a thovſand places of the Scripture, that unto a Chriſtian all his Sins and debts are acquitted, by the Grace and Mercy of God, that they are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, that they are covered, that they are not imputed, and that they are remitted and pardoned, that they are caſt as far from us, as the Eaſt from the Weſt; provided that there be no more Seed thereof, we need not look for any Fruit: That is to ſay, if there be no more Sin, there is no more anger of God, nor of death,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153299:8"/>and by conſequent that alſo there ought to be no more fear.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, By Faith we have the Word and the Promiſes of GOD, whereupon it is grounded: Among others this; <hi>Whoſo Believeth ſhall not Die, but is paſſed from Death to Life.</hi> Now this promiſe can no more fail, than He that gave it us: It is Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal; and all that God ſaith, is as ſure and permanent as Heaven and Earth: For this cauſe when we look into them, we ought in them to conſider the vertue and power of this Word, by the which they were once Created, and ever ſince pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and maintained in that eſtate wherein, we now ſee them; and to infer thereupon, that being of the ſame power and efficacy in all other things, nothing is, impoſſible nor uncertain of all that which God doth ſay and promiſe unto us. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as St. <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>Receiving His
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153299:8"/>holy Word by Faith in our Hearts, and the Promiſes which He hath made us, to give us Eternal Life, we ought to aſſure our ſelves of it, and take away all fear and apprehenſion of Death.</hi> What was the cauſe of the ruin of us and our Fore-fathers? Was it not becauſe they did decline from the Word of God, to follow their own Fancies and the Counſel of Satan? If then on the contrary we will cleave to it, without leaning any jot either to the right hand or to the left, we ſhall live by it, and in it. <hi>Hearken unto Me,</hi> ſaith GOD (<hi>ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by</hi> Iſaiah) <hi>and your Soul ſhall Live.</hi> And <hi>Zachary</hi> in his Song; <hi>He hath given us a knowledge of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> And St. <hi>Peter,</hi> ſpeaking to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, <hi>Thy Words are Words of Eternal Life.</hi> If GOD, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles, do aſſure us, that the Word of God received by a true Faith in our Hearts, doth there quicken, keeping and retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153299:9"/>it; What occaſion have we then to fear Death?</p>
               <p>Moreover, by Faith we dwell in Jeſus Chriſt, and have him dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in us, who having Life in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as his Father, doth quicken us, and all thoſe unto whom he doth communicate himſelf: Wherefore then being his Members, Fleſh of His Fleſh, and Bone of His Bones; in brief, being one with him, ſhall we fear Death? Hath not He pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over it, and not only for Himſelf, but alſo for us? <hi>He</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi>) <hi>who hath once overcome Death for us, will always overcome it in us.</hi> Hath not he beat down, diſpoſſeſſed, chaſed and ſpoiled <hi>Satan,</hi> the Prince and Lord of Death? Hath not he accompliſhed the Law; and by this perfect Obedience, which he hath born to God his <hi>Father,</hi> appeaſed his Anger, ſatisfied his Will, and aboliſhed the malediction of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153299:9"/>Law, which is nothing elſe but Death? Did not he die to make it die, when he roſe again? Hath not he broken and diſſipated all the Torments, plucked down the Gates of Hell, and triumphed over her and all her Power? Say not henceforth, faith St. <hi>Paul, who ſhall go up into Heaven, or who ſhall deſcend into the depths, for to bring Life unto us? For Jeſus Chriſt is dead, and riſen again from the dead, for to deliver us from death; and riſen again to reſtore us to Life: He is our Paſtor; and for this Reaſon we ought not to fear, that any Creature ſhould ſnatch us by Violence out of his Hands, or can hinder him from giving us Eternal Life. He is our Advocate, we ought not then to fear to be overthrown in Judgment; nor that by Sentence we ſhould be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to death; He is our Mediator, we need not to fear the Wrath of God; He is our Light, we not fear Darkneſs;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153299:10"/>He is our Shadow and our Clouds, we ought not then to fear the heat of the Fire Eternal, no more than did the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>the heat of the Sun in the Wilderneſs, being hidden under the Pillar. Let us then for theſe Reaſons forſake and caſt behind us all Fear of Death; which having had no Power nor Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage over the Head, ſhall have no Power over his Members.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, By Faith we have with Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt God his Father, and are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied and joined together with him, as he ſaith by his Prophet, I will mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thee if thou wilt promiſe me thy Faith: And Jeſus Chriſt in St. <hi>John, He that loveth me will keep my word, and I and my Father will come and dwell in him:</hi> For this Reaſon we are alſo called his Temples; becauſe we are conſecrated and dedicated unto him by his Holy Spirit, that he ſhould dwell in us. Now, ſeeing God is with us, we have the Original, the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153299:10"/>Fountain, the Cauſe, the Beginning, and the Author of Life; we have the great <hi>Jehovah,</hi> of whome all things depend, by whome all things are, and move, in whome the Angels, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angels, Principalities, the Heavens, and all the Elements conſiſt; we have him, from whome all Creatures, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and Inviſible, take their Life, and their Being, by the Participati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which they have with him: We have him who is the moſt Perfect, and moſt Soveraign Work-man of all things, who by his breath doth quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, and make them to Live, and by his power infinite doth preſerve them: We have, to make ſhort, Him who only can fatisfie, and by his Preſence cauſe that of Life, and of all other good things we ſhall have, and think we have enough: Shall we then fear Death in ſuch company? If as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, God is the Soul of our Soul, we cannot die but by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeparated from him; the which
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153299:11"/>
                  <hi>David</hi> doth confirm in one of his <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Thoſe ſhall periſh O Lord, who do depart and go from thee;</hi> which being conſidered, let us ſtrive only to keep him with us by Faith and Obedience; and beſides, let us take away all the fear which we may have of Death.</p>
               <p>Again, by Faith we have the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God: <hi>You are not Carnal,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> (writing to the <hi>Romans</hi>) <hi>but are Spiritual, for who hath not the Spirit of God is none of his.</hi> And elſe-where ſpeaking to the <hi>Galathians, Have you not the Spirit of God by Faith?</hi> Now this Spirit is the Spirit of Life; if God withdraws it from his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures they die, they periſh, and come ſuddenly to nught: On the contrary, when he pleaſeth to ſend and pour it upon them, he raiſeth and reſtoreth them in an inſtant; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as we ſee a Hen brooding of her Eggs, by a ſecret vertue doth diſcloſe and bring them to Life, albeit that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153299:11"/>before they were without ſence or feeling. Even ſo doth the Spirit of God, all Creatures by his Divine Power: He giveth teſtimony, and doth aſſure us in our Hearts that we are the Children of God, to the end that from him as from our Father, by a certain and aſſured hope we ſhould wait and look for Life: He is a pledge unto us for fear leſt we ſhould doubt. Having therefore ſuch ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of Life, having teſtimony from him, who being the Spirit of Truth cannot lie nor abuſe, having him himſelf who is the preſerver of all Creatures, ſhall we fear Death? It is as much as who ſhould fear the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at noon-day, the Spirit of him who hath raiſed again Jeſus Chriſt, and who hath up-held him becauſe he ſhould not be overcome of Death, being in us will quicken us alſo, ſaith Saint <hi>Paul;</hi> and will preſerve us from it; let us then put away all fear of it.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:153299:12"/>
               <p>Faith alſo cauſeth that God doth adopt and repute us for his Children: you are all Children of God by faith, ſaith St. <hi>Paul;</hi> and St. <hi>John,</hi> he hath given power to all thoſe that ſhall receive him, and believe in his Name, to be made the Children of God; then being Children, we are the Heirs and Co-heirs with Jeſus Chriſt; and we are by the means of this adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion certain once to come unto Life, unto the reſt, and unto the glory wherein we ſhall Reign Eternally with his Father. Moreover, being Children of God, we are of his Houſhold, and it is not in his Houſe where Death dwelleth, it is in Hell in the Devil's Houſe; in Heaven and the Place where God abides, there is an unſpeakable Light, ſo great a Beatitude and Happineſs, that in the Contemplation thereof, <hi>David</hi> crying out, ſaid, <hi>O how they are hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py that do inhabit and dwell in thy Houſe!</hi> And elſewhere, <hi>In this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153299:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>all my good, Lord that I may be near unto thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, being Children we are at Liberty, free from Sin, free from Death, free from the Condemnation and Rigour of the Law, freed from Service and Force of the Devil: what do we fear being then Children of God, and conſequently Brothers of Jeſus Chriſt? Is it poſſible that he can ever deny or abandon his Fleſh and Blood, or ſuffer them to die, having Power to ſave them? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore being the Children of God our Father, he loveth us with a Love un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeigned and Fatherly. And if, as ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> during the time that we were his Enemies, he had ſuch a care over us, that not ſparing his only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son, he hath delivered him over to Death to preſerve us from it, and to reconcile us unto himſelf, now that we are his Friends and in his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, will he not ſave us? Who is that Man, who conſidering theſe
<pb facs="tcp:153299:13"/>Reaſons, will not preſently aſſure himſelf, and caſt away all fear which he had of Death? That which alſo ought to aſſure us againſt Death, and take away all fear which we have of it, and of the Horrour and Anguiſh prepared for the reprobate and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, is our Calling; that God of his Grace hath vouchſafed to withdraw us out of the Darkneſs wherein we were, and to illuminate us by his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, teaching us by his Holy Word, wherein we ought to truſt, and wherein lyeth our Salvation; and ſo what we ought to do to pleaſe and obey him, to the end that walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his Law, and ſerving him in all Juſtice and Holineſs, we might after we have a little ſuffered in this World, be faithfully glorified with him in the end; for that which God beginneth he will accompliſh; and when he hath determined to call any one to him and to ſave him he never changeth his Counſel, neither doth
<pb facs="tcp:153299:13"/>repent himſelf of the good that he will do unto him. He us Unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and ſo ſtedfaſt in his Purpoſe and Determination, that that which he once Wills and Ordains, he doth execute without being turned from it. If then we feel in our ſelves that God hath given us the Grace to hear, to believe, and to love his Word, and to fly from and reject all that which is contrary to it, and to have an Affection to obſerve that which he commandeth us, and a diſlike, if haply by infirmity or otherwiſe, we chrnce to commit any thing againſt his Law: Let us not doubt but we are regenerate, elected, and prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinated to Eternal Life, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently out of danger of Death. Let us then take away all fear, and let us ſay with St. <hi>Paul, What ſhall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate us from the Love and Charity of God? What ſhall make us to think, that he hath not a will to ſave us? It ſhall not be Pain, Affliction, Hunger,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153299:14"/>Perſecution, nor Adverſity, nor Death, nor any Creature whatſoever ſhall make us to doubt that he doth not love us, in the favour of Jeſus Chriſt, and that having choſen, called and juſtified us in him, but that finally he will alſo glorify us by him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Sacraments which Jeſus Chriſt hath left us for the Confirmation of our Faith, ought likewiſe to aſſure and ſtrengthen us againſt the Fear of Death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Baptiſm by the which we are buried and die with Chriſt, that we may riſe again with him; in the which we are waſhed from all our ſins, and clothed with his Innocency, to the end, that preſenting our ſelves to the Father, ſo adorned and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the Robe of our Elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we may receive his Holy Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and be ſaved from the Deluge, wherein all the Infidels periſh, as <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> was in his time by the Ark. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving then the Promiſes of God, as we have ſaid before, and over and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153299:14"/>above his Sign and Seal, by the which he has bound himſelf, to render that Life to us, which we haveloſt by our Sin; wherefore then do we fear Death, doe we think that he will revoke, or that he will deny and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avow his own Sign and Seal.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Lord's Supper, where we take the Bread and the Wine, for to be received into the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and Participation of the Body and Blood of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and by Conſequent into the Fruits of them; that is, to have part in his Obedience, in his Juſtice, in his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction and Redemption, in the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament and new Alliance, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally in all the promiſes of God, the which by his Death have been rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, It remaineth now to conclude our purpoſe, and to infer upon the precedent things, that if we fear Death, it is for want of conſidering them, or if we do conſider them, it is for want of believing them; for
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:153299:15"/>there is no man ſo timerous, being firmly perſwaded of that which is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, but will take away all fear of Death, and will ſay with <hi>David, I ſhall not die but always live, to declare perpetually the Works of the Lord, and praiſe him.</hi> And who will not ſcorn at it with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and inſult upon it, ſaying, <hi>O Death where is thy Victory? Where is thy Sting? Where is thy Strength? Where is thy Terrour and Fear which Men had of thee?</hi> Jeſus Chriſt our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour perceiving the time of his Death draw near, ſaid, <hi>that in ſhort time he ſhould paſs from this World to go to his Father,</hi> calling Death a Paſſage; which ſhould greatly comfort us. We have almoſt all this opinion rooted in us, and it is that which doth ſo Diſcourage us, that it is a dangerous paſſage and uneaſie. Now for to take it from us, and to ſtir up our Hearts, he would needs paſs it before us, and as it were ſound the depth to the end, that we ſeeing that he
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:153299:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>did not ſtick at it, ſhould take Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage: As alſo we ſee before and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, the Prophets, Apoſtles, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, and other Holy Perſons have done it; who having paſſed it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any apprehenſion of Danger, and being eſcaped ſafe and well, do now rejoice with God, that they are got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to the Land, and to the Port where they did aſpire. Shall we then be ſuch Cowards? ſhall we be ſo faint hearted, and of ſuch tender and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feminate Courage, as to fear to go by a place ſo frequent, and a way ſo great and beaten, that Men go it, as ſaid ſome of the Ancients, Blindfold? Likewiſe we ſee that not one alone of thoſe that truſted in God, calling upon his aid, that put themſelves to paſs it, did ever miſcarry; when the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did fear at the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the <hi>Red-Sea, Moſes</hi> did ſhew unto them, <hi>that if they would truſt in God, they ſhould ſee his Glory and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er;</hi> which they did ſee, paſſing ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:153299:16"/>through the midſt of the danger, where their Enemies did periſh: So ſhall all the Faithful through the ſtraights of Death, provided that they commend themſelves to God, and do only ſet their truſt upon him. They being in the Deſarts, although they were bitten by the Serpents, yet were they preſerved from the danger in looking upon him, that <hi>Mofes</hi> had cauſed to be erected: So alſo, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the curſed and envious Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent hath tainted us with his Venom, yet ſhall we not die, if by faith we look upon Jeſus Chriſt Cruciſied. Let Death come, let it take us, let it bind us, yet ſhall we break the bonds as eaſily as did <hi>Sampſon</hi> thoſe of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines his Enemies; let it ſwallow and devour us as the Whale did <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> yet ſhall it fain to diſgorge and caſt us up again, if in the midſt of the depth we do remember God and call upon him. Let it bury us as it once did Jeſus Chriſt, yet ſhall we
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:153299:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>riſe again as he did, and it ſhall be impoſſible for this Tyrant to retain us under his Power. After having ſhewed how we ſhould arm our ſelves againſt the apprehenſions of Eternal Death: Let us alſo ſhew that we ought not only not to fear the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral but alſo deſire it; and when it pleaſeth God to ſend it unto us, to thank him for it, to rejoice at it, to embrace it, and to ſing for Joy; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be that we behold the Miſery, the Miſhaps and evils of this Life, from which it doth deliver us; or elſe the joy and contentment of eternal Life, whereto it doth bring us.</p>
               <p>As for the poverties, miſeries, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certitudes, accidents and mutabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of this Life, not only the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but alſo diverſe wiſe and great Philoſophers doth ſhew them unto us: And there is one amongſt them, who declaring the Original of the Greek Phraſe ſignifying Life, ſayeth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is, that Life
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:153299:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>hath been ſo called of the Greeks, becauſe of the violence of the aſſaults, exceſs, pains, and out-rages which therein we ſuffer, which are innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable both in Body and Soul.</p>
               <p>Our Bodies are ſubject to cold, to heat, to hunger, to thirſt, to time, to age, and to ſo many Diſeaſes, that there is no part but hath his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar infirmity: The feet are ſubject unto the gouts, the belly unto gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings, the ſides to pleuriſies, the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach to rawneſs, the lungs to the cough, the head to a thouſand Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes; we need but a ſpider or other little worm to kill us, we need but a hair or a crum to ſtrangle us: in ſum; the fleſh with all its ſtrength, is nothing elſe but graſs; Is it to day green and pleaſant? let but the Sithe paſs, it will cut down a thouſand leaves at once, which in an hour will be drie and withered. The Greeks do call the body of Man in their Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, <hi>Soma</hi> and <hi>Demas,</hi> whereof the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:153299:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>one is taken from a phraſe which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth to bind, and the other comes near to that which ſignifieth Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre, for to ſhew unto us in what eſtate and diſpoſition ſoever he be, he doth repreſent rather Death unto us than Life, and Servitude than Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. As for the Soul, it is firſt ſubject to all the evils and diſeaſes of the body; for it is unpoſſible if that be ill, but that for the conjunction and amity which is between them, it muſt endure and feel pain. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſhe hath her own diſtempers, as ignorance, ſin, miſtruſt, ſuſpicion, jealouſie, hatred, envy, love, luſt, ambition and paſſions, the which as tormentors, do hale her the one one way, the other another, as if they would pull it to pieces. I leave a million of importunities which ſhe hath, and which man taketh to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to his purpoſes, to live in reſt and at eaſe, to be in honour, to maintain his alliances and friendſhips,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:153299:18"/>to beware of his Enemies, to encreaſe his Houſe, to amintain and keep it in its greatneſs, the which do tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment us oft-times in ſuch ſort, that we can neither eat or ſleep at eaſe.</p>
               <p>And we muſt not think that there is any eſtate exempt from this miſery; begin at the higheſt Prince or Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour that ever was in the World, and ſo diſcourſing deſcend to the pooreſt begger that ever the Earth did bear, and you ſhall not find one content, neither the Artificer nor the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, nor the Advocate, nor the Gentleman, nor the Duke, nor the King; enter into their cloſets, there you ſhall often find them, as ſaid <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nander,</hi> laid upon their Beds with a mournful Voice, and pitiful, crying, <hi>Alas, alas. Valeri</hi> IX. ſpeaketh of a King, unto whom the Scepter and Diadem were offered; before he put it on his head, he took it in his hands, then having looked long upon it, he cryed out; <hi>O Diadem, if one knew the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:153299:18"/>miſeries and incumbrances which thou doeſt bring, there is no man that find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee upon the ground, would once take thee up;</hi> ſhewing by that excla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, that the Life of Kings is leſs happy than that of private Perſons. <hi>Tyberius Caeſar,</hi> under whom Chriſt was crucified, and who commanded that he ſhould be worſhipped as a God alſo, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> records it, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Death of <hi>Auguſtus</hi> his Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour, who by will had left him Heir, as well of his Goods as of the Empire; which being offered him by the Senate, according to cuſtom, doubted a great while whether he might accept of it, by reaſon of the fear that he had of the weight of this charge, and of the pain that he was to ſuffer in the undergoing of it. <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocleſian</hi> after he had held the Empire ſome twenty years, left it of his own accord, and choſe for the reſt of his time to live a peaceable and domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Life; wherein after the great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:153299:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>and ſtorms of trouble which he had during the time of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, he found the reſt to be ſo ſweet and pleaſing, and his mind ſo contented and freed, that many times amongſt his familiars he did witneſs, that the time had never ſeemed ſo good to him, nor his Sun-ſhine days ſo pleaſant; ſhewing by theſe words how he did abhor the Imperial Life, although that few Emperors before or after him had had ſuch Honours in Victories, and other proſperities as he had.</p>
               <p>Theſe Examples do ſufficiently ſhew, that the Life of Kings is not ſo happy, as ſome men ſometimes eſteem them, more by errour than by reaſon; and they are far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at quiet and without trouble: For by how much a Tree is planted and ſeated in a higher place, by ſo much the more is it ſubject to the wind; ſo alſo are the great men more than the commons, to divers fortunes
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:153299:19"/>and accidents; the Thunder-bolts and the Tempeſts fall ordinarily in high places, ſo do the greateſt mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes upon Men of ſtate and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown.</p>
               <p>And if in this World the Eſtates which we eſteem moſt of are ſubject to ſo many mis-haps, what may we think of others, which we our ſelves by reaſon of the diſcommodities which are joyned unto them, do fly from and eſteem unhappy? So we ſee that there is not any eſtate, that of it ſelf doth make a body happy or contented; and as in Eſtates, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the common Miſeries, every one hath his own particular; ſo alſo have all the Ages of Man evils which are proper unto them.</p>
               <p>In his Child-hood he is full of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, without Vertue, without Underſtanding, without the uſe of Reaſon and Speech, and without Wit; and he muſt be fifteen years old before he is capable to know
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:153299:20"/>only what Eſtate is fitteſt for him; wherein often-times he deceives him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, chuſing that whereunto he is leaſt fit.</p>
               <p>Is he come into his Youth? he is raſh, adventurous, fooliſh, paſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, voluptuous, prodigal, a drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard, a gameſter, quarrelſom; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it happeneth oft, that in this age he falleth into great inconveniences and dangers, to be Impriſoned, to be Hanged, to loſe his Goods, and even to bring his Parents with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row to the Grave.</p>
               <p>When this great heat by little and little begins to cool and diminiſh; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat he waxeth a perfect Man; then he muſt labour Night and Day for to entertain his Houſe, nouriſh his Children, and provide for them for time to come: he is Beſieged, now with Defire and Covetouſneſs, then with Fear, leſt his Children ſhould remain unprovided for, leſt they ſhould behave themſelves ill,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:153299:20"/>and leſt they ſhould do ſome dis-ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to their Houſe.</p>
               <p>The Age of Vertue and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection declining, behold in our ſight old Age comes creeping on, in the which Man is ſickly, unweildy, cold and forſaken; and as among the Seaſons of the Year, the laſt is Winter, and the moſt troubleſome; ſo amongſt all the Ages of Man, is the old Age.</p>
               <p>That which I have ſaid, is not the hundredth part of all the Evils whereunto the Sick Man is ſubject; and nevertheleſs that little which we have ſpoken of it, is ſufficient to ſhew that in all Eſtates and in all Ages, it is miſerable; and as ſaid <hi>Merander, Life and Miſery are two Twins; for they are born and grow, they are nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed and live always together.</hi> Which Nature teacheth us in two things: <hi>Firſt,</hi> in that the little Children <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> into the World, they always <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> preſaging the Evil which
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:153299:21"/>they are to endure if they live long: <hi>Secondly,</hi> in that coming forth of their Mothers Belly, they are all bathed in Blood, and are more like unto a dead Man, whoſe Throat had been lately out by Murtherers, then to any thing elſe. Two ancient Philoſophers conſidering theſe things ſaid the one, <hi>That God did love thoſe which he takes out of this World in their Child-hood:</hi> The other; <hi>That it were good never to be Born, or elſe to die preſently.</hi> Surely it is a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thing, and which ſheweth well that we have want of Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that although Life were never ſo ugly and dis-figured, and that in all her parts there were neither Grace nor Beauty that could commend it, we nevertheleſs ſhould be ſo in love with it, that we always deſire to keep it, and never to change. But we are much abuſed, for it is more uncertain then it is miſerable: For to ſhew us the uncertainty of it, the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:153299:21"/>Ancients called it <hi>a Shadow, and a Dream;</hi> which are the two things in the World, the moſt vain and leaſt fixed. <hi>Pythagoras</hi> being once demanded what humane Life was, ſpake never a word; for his cuſtom was to anſwer and inſtruct more by Signs than by Words; but went into a Chamber, and came forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain preſently: Signifying, <hi>That the Life of Man is but an entring in, and going out.</hi> And Jeſus Chriſt exhorteth us to Watch, and grounds Himſelf upon nothing elſe, but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the inconſtancy and uncertainty of this Life: <hi>Watch,</hi> ſaith He, <hi>for you know not at what Hour the Lord will come.</hi> And who is that Man, in how good diſpoſition and happineſs ſoever he be, that can promiſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf continue in it but a day? Thoſe 18 Men in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> doubted of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, when in an inſtant they were deſtroyed by the ruins of the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of <hi>Syloe.</hi> In the time of the Flood,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:153299:22"/>they did Build, and made Marriages and Banquets; when ſuddenly, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the expectation and opinion of all the World, the Rain fell in clear Weather; which Rain did o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verflow the whole Earth. The rich Man, whereof mention is made in the Twelfth of <hi>Luke,</hi> though he was very ſecure; who having ſo much Wealth that he know not where to Whord it, made account to give himſelf to Pleaſure, and to live af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that time at his eaſe; when while he was ſtanding upon theſe terms, behold the Serjeant of GOD comes day, to give up an account unto him, of all the precious things and goods which he had left, and which he had gathered with ſuch great la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</p>
               <p>But it is labour loſt to go about to prove a thing ſo manifeſt, and which we experiment and ſee daily: For in this VVorld there is nothing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:153299:22"/>more ordinary, nor more frequent, then that which <hi>Ovid</hi> ſaith, <hi>That the Life of Man, and all humane things are hanged, and do hold but by a little Thred.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let us behold then, ſeeing on the one ſide the great Evils whereof it is full, and on the other ſide the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy of the good which it hath; if we have great occaſion to deſire God, that he would prolong it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us; or to complain or diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent our ſelves at Death, when it taketh it away from us? VVe have underſtood the evils from the which Death doth deliver us; let us now come to conſider the good which it bringeth unto us, from thence we ſhall yet better know, that we ought not only not to fear, ſhun, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void it, but alſo deſire it with all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; for one of the Goods only which we enjoy by Deaths means, is greater than all thoſe which we
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:153299:23"/>can have in the VVorld, living in it for ever.</p>
               <p>By it firſt we reſt, as ſaith St. <hi>John</hi> is his <hi>Apocalyps.</hi> And after that we have endured, and are almoſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed with innumerable troubles and labours, Dying, our Spirit go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into Heaven, and our Body into the Earth, as into a Bed, there for to reſt and refreſh it ſelf. The poor Artificers are ſo glad when Evening draws near, and that it is almoſt Night, that they may be paid for their Labour, and go home to reſt themſelves; or when after they have laboured the ſix Days in the Week, that <hi>Sunday</hi> comes, when they hope to reſt and refreſh themſelves, and recover the force and vigour, as well of their Bodies as of their Minds; we ought not to be leſs joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful when the time of our Death draweth near, which we ought to wait for, and deſire as a Holy-day; in the which we hope to reſt, and by
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:153299:23"/>the pleaſure which therein we take, preſently forget all the ſorrows and troubles which we have had in this World. The end of all that we do, and of that which we purpoſe, Is it not our Reſt? Why do we gather Goods with a thouſand troubles, and as many dangers? Why do we Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy? Why do we Fight? Why do we Labour? Why do we all other things? Is it not by that means to come to eaſe and to a reſt, which we pretend and ſeek as a ſoveraign good? VVhat is the principal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward which God doth promiſe to his People, and to all thoſe that ſerve him Faithfully; Is it not a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual reſt, where into he himſelf is entred ſince the Creation of the VVorld? VVhen we do Pray unto Him that <hi>His Kingdom come;</hi> Is it peace and reſt? <hi>Finally,</hi> what we do hope for at his Hands, Is it not that? Then the reſt which God hath
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:153299:24"/>promiſed us, which we demand of him, which we wait for, and which we do purpoſe as the end and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of all that we do and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, is given us by no other means, but by Death. Some ſeek for it in their Goods, which they love, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing there to find it; others in Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, others in Voluptuouſneſs and wordly Pleaſures: But all this is but an abuſe; for it is found no where but in Death, which we ought more to Love for this reaſon, than the Wordling doth his Pleaſure, the Covetous Man his Treaſure, the Scholar his Books, or the Ambitious his Humours; by reaſon that in one Hour it putteth into our hands, and gives us the enjoying of Goods, which they cannot find by great Labour all their life time, in the aforeſaid things. Furthermore, Death cauſeth that by it we are content, fatisfied, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry happy. <hi>Happy are thoſe which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part in the Faith of our Lord,</hi> ſaith
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:153299:24"/>St. <hi>John.</hi> Then is this Bleſſedneſs the ſoveraign good where unto we aſpire, and which we cannot find in this World, where we are never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. If we have Goods, we deſire Knowledge; if we have Knowledge, we deſire Honours; if we have Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, we deſire Health; if we have Health, we deſire to be Young: Briefly, we always want ſomething which we ſeek after, and when we cannot get it, that is a cauſe of grudging and diſcontentment: But then ſhall we be fully ſatisfied, as ſaith <hi>David, When by Death we are come to the Kingdom of God, and his Glory hath appeared unto us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In it are all things; it is the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign good which doth compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend all other; therefore when we ſhall have it, our appetite and deſire ſhall reſt in it; we ſhall reſt there without going any further, without demanding or ſeeking for any thing elſe. Then ſhall be accompliſhed
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:153299:25"/>that which Jeſus Chriſt hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to all his Faithful, who, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving in him with an entire Faith, and ſuch a one as God requires in his Word, will raiſe up in their Hearts a Spring of Water of Life, ſpringing to Life Eternal. We ſhall no more fear any thing, being no more in danger; we ſhall deſire no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, having all in our poſſeſſion; we ſhall hope for nothing, for all Promiſes ſhall be accompliſhed; we ſhall no more ask any thing, for we ſhall have no more need; God ſhall be all in all. If we will be rich, we ſhall then have Him that doth in rich all thoſe that call upon His Holy Name; if we will be wiſe, we ſhall have the Heavenly Wiſdom; if we will be mighty, we ſhall have the Almighty; if we deſire to be good, we ſhall have the only excellent Good; if we will be fair, we ſhall have the great Architect, and perfect Workman of all things; If we will
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:153299:25"/>be healthful and live long, we ſhall have the Eternal.</p>
               <p>All our Senſes ſhall be raviſhed with the greatneſs of the Pleaſures which they ſhall have and feel. Our Eyes ſeeing the great, ſumptuous, and magnificent Pallace of our God, ſeeing the perfect and ſoveraigne Beauty of His bright ſhining Face: Seeing the Sun of Juſtice, the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Water of Life, the Tree of Life, the Paradice, that is to ſay, the pleaſant Garden of our GOD, His fair and noble company of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, of Apoſtles, Patriarchs, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, and of all the bleſſed Spirits And if the only ſight of Jeſus Chriſt transfigured in the Mountain, was of ſuch great power, that St. <hi>Peter,</hi> (all other things forgotten) in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, was thereby tranſported out of himſelf, and deſired ſo to remain perpetually: What may we think of the joy and pleaſure that he receives who ſeeth Jeſus Chriſt glorified, and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:153299:26"/>with him his Father, his Holy Spirit, and all the aforeſaid Aſſembly? <hi>Eye hath not ſeen, Ear hath not heard, Heart hath never conceived, the good, the pleaſure, the reſt, and the content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, prepared for thoſe which God hath Elected to Salvation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Ears ſhall likewiſe be ravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, hearing the Diſcourſes and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the incomprehenſible Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of our God: Again, the good Muſick, the ſweet and pleaſant ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of the Angels and Saints reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Him, which Sing without ceaſing, <hi>To the Holy, Holy, Holy God of Hoſts, be Honour and Glory, for ever and ever. Selomon</hi> upon the Earth raviſhed the People, and made them aſtoniſhed at the great Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Knowledge that was in him. So did Jeſus Chriſt alſo when He Preached. What can he then now do in Heaven, where all the great treaſures of his divine Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence are unfolded and laid open?
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:153299:26"/>When <hi>Aeſchines</hi> had repeated to the <hi>Rhodians</hi> the Oration of <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> for the which he was Baniſhed, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they marvelled at it, <hi>What would you have done</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>if you had heard him pronounce it?</hi> We alſo that are ſo raviſhed only with the reading of the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> when we ſhall hear Jeſus Chriſt pronounce them, and with open Mouth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe continually with us; ſhall we not ſtand before him. In the like extaſie as was S. <hi>Paul,</hi> being raviſhed into the third Heavens? Shall we not have our Eyes ſetled with conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual looking upon our Maſter, and our Ears always attentive to hearken unto him? <hi>Plato</hi> gave God thanks for Three things; for that he was a Man, for that he was a Grecian, for that he had been ſo happy as to hear <hi>Socrates.</hi> And ſhall not we give him thanks for that we are Chriſtians, for that we are Heavenly, and for that by the means of Death, we hope
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:153299:27"/>Eternally to hear the Wiſdom of God?</p>
               <p>We have ſaid, what we ſhall ſee and hear; and now what ſhall we taſte? We ſhall be ſet at the Table of our Lord, where we ſhall have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of all good things. It ſhall be covered with meats that he hath prepared, and reſerved a long while ſince, for that banquet; we ſhall there be fed with the bread of Angels; we ſhall be made to drink in Brooks of Pleaſure; we ſhall be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with all good things; we ſhall be always at Nuptials, and in an inſtant we ſhall forget all the delights of the Earth, having taſted thoſe of Heaven; as did the Companions of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes</hi> all other meats, when they had eaten <hi>Lotos</hi> ſo celebrated by <hi>Homer.</hi> It is an other manner of <hi>Manna</hi> than that of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for they waxed weary of it, and were ſorry in the deſert, that they had loſt the Quails and Fleſh pots of <hi>Egypt.</hi> But
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:153299:27"/>we in Heaven, at the firſt taſte of the meats, which there ſhall be ſerved us, ſhall looſe then all appetite to the Pleaſures of this World. We have hear eaten of the fruits of the Tree of Knowledge of good and evil, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Command of the Phyſitian. Whereupon followed the Sickneſs and Death of all. But in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, and of Paradiſe, we ſhall eat of the Fruit of the Tree of Life, which ſhall always keep us young and freſh; and which is more, will make us incorruptible and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal. This is that which we ſhall taſte; what then ſhall we ſmell? A Hall of Perfumes, the Garments of the Bride and the Bridegroom, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumed with all odoriferous and fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant things. It ſhall be then that he Church ſhall Triumph, and that the Vine being bloſſom'd, ſhall give ſuch a pleaſant odour that the whole Heavens ſhall be filled with it.</p>
               <p>There ſhall be no ſtink, for there
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:153299:28"/>ſhall be no Corruption; we ſhall there plainly ſmell the ſweetneſs of the Sacrifice, which Jeſus Chriſt made for us on Earth, ſo great and pleaſant, that the Father for the Pleaſure which he took in it, was reconciled with the world, and his anger towards us hath been appeaſed. What a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Sacrifice, and precious Incenſe is alſo the praiſes of the Saints, who with one accord do glorifie God, and ſanctifie his holy Name? More over what an odour gives that fair flower ſprung from the root and ſap of Jeſs now that it is in its force and ſtrength To conclude, we cannot miſs then to ſmell good odours; for our Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall then be paſt, and we ſhall be in a perpetual ſpring time, where in all things ſhall grow and flouriſh for the Delectation and Pleaſures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Church. For to ſatisfie our d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſire, and content all our affection we ſhall touch no more, neither ſhat we be touched of any thing that m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:153299:28"/>hurt us. We ſhall be gathered up by Jeſus Chriſt our Lord and Saviour, who will come at the entrance to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us, ſaying, <hi>Come hither faithful Servant, thou haſt ſerved me faithfully in the World, while thou haſt been in the World; enter now into the Joy and reſt of the Lord.</hi> He will kiſs and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace us, and will keep us near to his Perſon, without ſuffering us to depart or go far from it.</p>
               <p>Now if the greateſt good, and that unto the which all others are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, be this felicity, which doth conſiſt in a poſſeſſion and enjoying of all good, to the contentment of our Will, and of all our ſenſes, with what a deſire ſhould we wait for Death, by the which we attain it?</p>
               <p>Moreover, Death doth deliver us out of all dangers: In this World night and day, within and without we are always in fear of peril. Our Life is a cruel and bloody War, we have a great many Enemies that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:153299:29"/>us continually, and do aſſay by all means to deſtroy us: The Devils Watch for us, and ceaſe not compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing about like devouring Lyons, and as ravening Wolves, to ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they cannot ſurprize us, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry us away; the World ſometimes by enticings, and allurements; ſome time by threats and violence, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to try and turn us out of the right way. Our Fleſh on the other ſide, doth flatter us, and the better to undermine us, with great cunning doth propound and lay before us, things wherein we have moſt delight, It weepeth alſo ſometimes, to ſtir us up to pity it, all to the intent to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win us, and cauſe us in all points to yield unto it, and that it may maſter us.</p>
               <p>Now if we conſider our infirmity, our ſtupidity and negligence, the little wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs and watchfulneſs that is in us
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:153299:29"/>we may judge in what danger we live It is impoſſible that we ſhould live in this World among ſo many that are infected, and that with ſo great a Contagion, without falling often in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Sickneſs. Is it poſſible that we ſhould ſo often grapple with ſuch ſtrong and mighty Enemies, without being ſometimes ſtaggered and over-thrown? Is it poſſible that we ſhould go in ſuch durty and muddy ways, without being defiled? We ſee it in good Saints of old time, who could not govern themſelves ſo well, but the ſerpent who always dogs us at the heels, hath reached them with his venom; but that they have fallen in divers faults, ſome in incredulity, others in idolatry, others in adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, others in exceſs and drunkenneſs, others in murthers; there is none of them but hath his fall, yea ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſo great and heavy, that they had been altogether bruiſed, if God
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:153299:30"/>had not upheld them with his hand. Ought not we then follow the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and as he did cry. Who ſhall deliver us from theſe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers wherein wherein we live, while our Soul is in this miſerable and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal body? Let us confeſs that it is our gain, and profit for to die, that by death we may be fully delivered from all mortal things.</p>
               <p>Again, death put us in full poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all the promiſes of God, and of thoſe good things which Jeſus Chriſt hath purchaſed for us, and that we hope for him. He in dying hath freed us, and purchaſed our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and nevertheleſs we ſee our ſelves ſtill in great ſcrvitude.</p>
               <p>We are Kings, Lords, Judges, hers of God, co-heirs with Jeſus Chriſt the Prince of Heaven and Earth, yet it ſeems not ſo, while we live this World; for there we are beaten and uſed like ſervants, like children under age, we have as yet
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:153299:30"/>no uſe nor managing of our goods. Kings and great Lords tho' we be, we are often in ſuch neceſſity, that we have neither Bread to eat, nor Water to drink, nor Wool to cover us. Moreover Jeſus Chriſt hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed for us the Grace of God, a perfect Juſtice, life Eternal, an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Incorruption, glory and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue to our Bodies, and to our Souls an aſſured peace and quietneſs, a joy and a contentment; but this good hath not yet been delivered unto us, for oftentimes we experiment the Wrath and Judgment of God; we ſeel the concupiſcences and vicious deſires of our fleſh.</p>
               <p>In our bodies their is Corruption, Mortality and Weakneſs, and in our ſpirit, Troubles, Anguiſh, and as it were a ſtudious and inteſtine war between our good and bad deſires, which fight the one againſt the other, and becauſe theſe evils are more grievous, ſo are the aboveſaid goods
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:153299:31"/>more great, and more to be deſired. If then, altho' they be already pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed for us, and that they be ours, we nevertheleſs cannot come to the poſſeſſion of them but by death, are not we for this reaſon much bound unto it? Ought not we to love and deſire it? The children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> being arrived at the River of <hi>Jordan,</hi> ſeeing on the other ſide thereof the fruitful Land which god had promiſed them, and that being paſſed, they ſhould begin to enjoy it and to reſt, had they not great cauſe to rejoyce, and to paſs the River with great alacrity? And why not we, when we ſhall come neer unto death, that is to ſay to the paſſage, beyond the which is our Country, our Houſe, our city, our Friends, and Kinsfolks, our Reſt, our Joy, and our Pleaſure? The Child who during the time of his minority hath alwaies lived in fear and baſe ſervitude, doth he not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce when he ſeeth the day coming
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:153299:31"/>wherein he doth hope to have liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and quietly to enjoy his goods? So ought every faithful man, ſeeing the day of his death draw near, in the which he ſhall be put in poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all the goods which God hath given him, and the gift wholly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned.</p>
               <p>When a man that hath undertak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en ſome long and tedious Journey, having travelled many daies, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wearied on the way, ſeeth the gate of the Town whether he goes, doth he not rejoyce, and as it were leap for joy? Doth he not give God thanks going into the Town, that it hath pleaſed him to conduct and bring him ſafely thither? Now ever ſince we were born, we have alwaies been in this world as ſtrangers, we have done nothing elſe but travel in this low place, as in a great deſert, we have here wearied our ſelves; then ſeeing death neer unto us, that is to ſay, the gate whereby we muſt
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:153299:32"/>enter into the Kindom of our God, and the ſtairs whereby we muſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend unto his Holy Mountain, have we not occaſion to conſolate our ſelves, and to leap for joy, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that we are almoſt arrived at the place, where we hope to reſt perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually: If poor <hi>Adam</hi> being driven out of the earthly Paradiſe, after he had taſted of the miſeries whereinto he precipitates himſelf by his ſin, had been called thither again, and ſet in his firſt Eſtate, what occaſion ſhould he have had to rejoyce? And we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, who after ſo many and divers af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, are called out by God, by the means of death, into no Earthly but Heavenly Paradiſe, not <hi>Adams,</hi> but Gods, where there is no Sin, where there is no Serpent, where there is no forbidding, in ſhort where there is no fear nor ſhame. When <hi>Noah</hi> after the flood, and falling of the waters which had broken and torn all, began to ſee the firm land
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:153299:32"/>he did rejoyce, and for joy ſacrificed to God for a thankſgiving; altho' it was accurſed, and brought forth thornes and thiſtles as before. What more great occaſion ſhall we have, when after the great flouds, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations which we have in this world, we ſhall begin to ſee and ſalute the Land of the living, the bleſſed Land, the land that was promiſed to the good, the Land flowing with Milk and Honey, and all ſweet and ſavory things? When <hi>Joſeph</hi> after he had a long time been priſoner in great ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity, ſuddenly without thinking thereon, was raiſed to ſuch dignity, that he was next the King in Egypt, making Laws and Ordinances, for to diſpoſe the State and Kingdom; had not he matter of Conſolation?</p>
               <p>We have no leſs, but much more, when after our Priſons, Captivities, Servitudes, Baniſhments, and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other afflictions which we ſuffer in this World, we by death are in a
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:153299:33"/>moment lifted up from the dunghill into Heaven, there to reign with Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and to be partakers of his Glory, of his Honour, of his Faith, of his Reſt, and of his Table.</p>
               <p>Was it not a great joy to the Jews, who had been captives three ſcore years in <hi>Babylon,</hi> amongſt the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters in great miſery, deprived of the uſe and benefit of ſpiritual things, ſuch as to aſſemble together to praiſe God, and to hear his Word, and to do other things appertaining to the office of a Chriſtian; weeping ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times when they were by themſelves, and hanging up their Harps and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, through grief that they could not ſerve God according to their deſires, nor ſing his praiſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the ſtrangers; was it not a great joy then in theſe circumſtances to have the Kings letters to return into their country, build their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? and there according to their ancient manner, in all Liberty, ſerve
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:153299:33"/>praiſe and worſhip their God; and is it leſs to us, when after a long and tedious captivity that we have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured in this world, converſing with Idolaters, Unbelievers, Blaſphemers, deſpiſers of God and of his Word; we are delivered and have our paſ-port to go into this celeſtial <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and into the holy Temple of our God, there for to praiſe him perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, and in beholding his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to glorifie and ſanctifie his holy Name?</p>
               <p>Death is alſo to be deſired by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that with out ſorrows in alſo ends our mourning; we in this world are alwaies ſad, heavy, and melancholy. In it we weep, we ſigh and alwaies wear the black weed: But when by death we go forth of it, to go into the Houſe of our Bridegroom, we put off and leave the mourning weed for to take our goodly and and ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous a biliments, and everlaſting joy ſhall be powred on thoſe which have
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:153299:34"/>been the faithful ſervants of God, and then ſhall be accompliſhed that which hath been promiſed them. You that do weep in this world are hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, for you ſhall laugh: there ſhall be no more grief, nor complaining, nor tears; for God at our coming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Kingdom will wipe them away from our eyes, we ſhall be comforted, and we ſhall reſt in <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, as did <hi>Lazarus,</hi> there ſhall be no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther queſtion but of ſinging and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every one to our Souls.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Praiſe thou the Lord, O my Soul! and all that is within me praiſe his Holy Name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So to the Harpe and other inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Go to, a wake that you may now be ſet up again in the eſtate to ſerve God, and praiſe him for his goodneſs, ſay to all the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O! give thanks unto the Lord, and call upon his Name, O! let your ſongs be of him and praiſe him, and let your talking be of all his wondrous works.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:153299:34"/>
               <p>Say to all creatures, bleſs the Lord in all his works, praiſe and exalt his Name. Bleſs God ye Angels of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, Sun, Moon, Fire, Aire, Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Earth, Trees, and Beaſts. A maid that hath long time been betro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed, deſires that the day of her Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage were come, and when it is come ſhe rejoyceth, ſeeing that ſhe ſhall ſoon be brought to her Husbands Houſe to dwell perpetually with him; we ought alſo to comfort our ſelves, when the time draws near that our Lord muſt come; and we ought to attend him waking as did the five wiſe Virgins, that ſo ſoon as he ſhall be come, we may go in to the wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with him, and that the gate be not ſhut againſt us, as it was againſt the five fooliſh, becauſe they were fallen aſleep.</p>
               <p>Another reaſon why death is to be wiſhed for, is that it cauſeth us to ſee our friend and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, of whom we have as yet ſeen but the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:153299:35"/>Picture. The Prophets and Apoſtles have deſcribed him unto us ſo fair of ſuch a comely Stature, ſo Courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſo Vertuous, ſo Loyal, ſo Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, ſo Lovely, ſo Noble, ſo Rich, ſo loving of Us, that for our ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he did abandon his own life, which ought more to move us then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing. Where is that Perſon, who having heard of ſo many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections to be in his friend, would not burn, and be altogether tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with deſire and affection to ſee him? If our King, or ſome Prince of renown comes into our Country, we deſire to ſee him, becauſe of the report which we have heard of his Vertue and Valour. If <hi>Hercules, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exander</hi> the great, <hi>Caeſar Cato,</hi> of whom we ſo much commend the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Pictures, were now in this world we would through curioſity go a hundred Miles to ſee them; with what an affection then ſhould we aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire to that day, in the which we
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:153299:35"/>ſhall face to face ſee and behold that ſo mighty Prince, who with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible force hath broken the head of all our Enemies; who like unto a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant <hi>Joſua,</hi> in deſpite of them hath brought us through the dangers, and conducted us into the land which God promiſed us? What a pleaſure ſhall it be to us to ſee him glorious, and in triumphant array, and round about him the goodly trophees of his great victories ſet up? It is ſaid that when <hi>Alexander</hi> had overcome <hi>Darius</hi> King of the Perſians, entring into the place where he made his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence. He ſits down in his Throne, and that preſently a Greek Grentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of his Company began to weep for joy in ſpeaking theſe words. O happy day in the which we ſee our King victorious againſt the Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and their pride trodden under foot! O that all <hi>Greece</hi> had now the ſight and the pleaſure of this Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle. Think what joy it will be alſo
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:153299:36"/>to every faithful Man, to ſee Jeſus Chriſt in his Royal Seat, holding un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Feet all his Enemies and ours, but eſpecially the Serpent whoſe head is already broken, and now he doth nothing elſe but wag his Tail, wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his ſinal end, which ſhall be at the day of Judgment. Many Kings and Princes did with great affection deſire to ſee him when he was on Earth in the form of a Servant. And <hi>Simeon</hi> becauſe he ſaw him ſo, did ſo rejoice, and was ſo ſatisfied, that he feared no more to die: Ought hot we more to deſire to ſee him in Heaven in a Kingly Robe, with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, greatneſs, majeſty and pomp, and in the ſtate of a Lord? The Queen of <hi>Sheba,</hi> who being induced by the rumour which was ſpred over all the Earth of the great Court of King <hi>Solomon,</hi> came running thither, from the fartheſt part of the South, to ſee him, and to hear his wiſdom; and after ſhe had diligently conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:153299:36"/>his great and marvellous Wiſdom; the order, the ſplendor, and ſtate of his Houſe, ſtood all aſtoniſhed, and with great admiration, ſaid, <hi>O how happy are the Servants of thy Houſe, who may ſee thy Face every day, and hear thy Divine Speeches?</hi> Let us ſay alſo, <hi>O thrice and four times happy are the Faithful, who dying go directly to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to behold the Face of Jeſus Chriſt, who is greater than</hi> Solomon: For the only contemplation of it, makes man content in every point; in taking from us the memory and feeling of all other pleaſures, cauſeth that we cannot, nor will not turn our eyes and Thoughts from it. Now Death doth not only cauſe us to ſee Jeſus Chriſt, but maketh us with him to behold the Angels, the Patriarks, the Prophets, the Apoſtles, the Martyrs, which have been ſingular in graces and vertues. And if any Man that hath a Heart towards God, deſires to ſee the Church well ordered in this
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:153299:37"/>World, and preferreth it to all that can be given him; albeit, the order is never ſo great, yet there will be many things more to be deſired; with what vehemence and heat then ſhould he wiſh to ſee it in Heaven, without ſpot or wrinkle, ſhining like the Sun, clothed in Robes as white as Snow, ſet forth in Nuptial Order?</p>
               <p>The laſt Reaſon, for the which we ought to deſire Death, is, that by it our Spirit being parted from the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which doth clog it, is more at liberty, and more capable to look into the Myſteries of God. We live all in this World with a natural deſire to know; therefore it is that for our contentment, we ſeek always to hear and ſee ſome Novelties; now is it not poſſible that here beneath we ſhould come to any great knowledg, chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the truth, as well becauſe that of it ſelf it is obſcure and hard to know; as alſo, for the Cares, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbations, Afflictions, Paſſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:153299:37"/>wherewith our mind is intangled and hindred, whilſt it is in our Bodies, which are unto it as duſt in a Man's Eye, which doth hinder it from diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning any thing underſtandingly. This is the Reaſon wherefore God ſaith unto <hi>Moſes, That whilſt we live we cannot ſee it clearly;</hi> for the which alſo S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>That we know but in part;</hi> and S. <hi>John, That we ſee the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of our god, but as it were in a Glaſs, or through a Window; but when our Soul ſhall be parted from this Body, and the vail taken away which blindeth her Eyes, then ſhall it behold and ſee God Face to Face, then ſhall it have the perfect Knowlede of him and of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt his Son, and in it Eternal Life. We ſhall behold that which now we Worſhip; for we ſhall enter into the Sanctuary of our Lord, and there ſhall look on him without ceaſing, the Propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation and the Cherubins: Nothing neither of the Law nor the Goſpel ſhall be any more unknown or hid from us. God
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:153299:38"/>will ſhew unto us.</hi> God will ſhew un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us as unto his Friends and Famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, all the Riches of his Houſe; he will talk Friendly with us, and will impart all unto us. An ancient Man turning from Merchandiſe, and being entred into the Hall, where <hi>Demetri</hi> IX. and <hi>Phalere</hi> IX. read; when he had heard him a little while, begins to complain, and ſaid, <hi>O unhappy Man that I am, have the Goods of this World been the Cauſe that I have been ſo long deprived of ſuch good things at theſe?</hi> Let us alſo ſay, <hi>O Miſerable Life, will thou laſt much longer? wilt thou not ſhortly let us go whither we aſpire? which is the School of our god. Muſt we loſe ſo many days? Happy Death wilt thou not haſten to bring us thither?</hi> We ſee by theſe Reaſons what occaſion we have to fear, flie from, and complain of Death, which is a reſt and ſleep moſt delightful above all other; for there is no noiſe nor dreams to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or interupt it: it is a holſom Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:153299:38"/>which being ſwallowed, doth heal us of all Diſeaſes, and taketh all pain from us. Which <hi>Socrates</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, after he had drunk the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon by the commandment of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians,</hi> who had unjuſtly condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him to die, when the venom was diſperſed in his Members, and his Friend <hi>Crito</hi> a little before he gave up the Ghoſt, had asked him, if he would command him nothing; <hi>no,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>but that thou offer Sacrifice to</hi> Eſculapi IX. <hi>the God of Phyſiek, to give him thanks; for I never took a Medicine of ſuch great force, nor which wrought bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> It is a great ſhame that theſe <hi>Pagans</hi> in their Ignorance and Infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity ſeem to be better inſtructed and more vertuous then we are; for we fear Death, and flie from it, as an evil thing, and they hold and eſteem it as an incomperable good. <hi>Epami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nondas</hi> at the hour of his Death per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving his Friends about his Bed weeping, comforted them, ſaying.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:153299:39"/>
                  <hi>Rejoice O my Friends, for your Friend</hi> Epaminondas <hi>is going to begin to Live.</hi> Is Death then an Evil, which hath nothing elſe of that which we eſteem Death, but the Name and Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for indeed it is a Life? Alſo is this life a good, which hath but the Name of it, for in effect it is a very Death? Both the one and the other, as ſaith Saint <hi>John Chryſoſtom,</hi> is mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and have both falſe Faces. Life which is ſo evil favoured hath the fair, which maketh it to be feared and hated. When it preſents it ſelf unto us ſo mask'd, at the firſt it ſeems fearful; but if we put up the mask we ſhall find it underneath ſo fair and Beautiful, that preſently we ſhall be inflamed with the Love of it. Let us then take away this vain fear of Death; let us believe that which is true, that it is the greateſt good that can happen unto us. That which anciently <hi>Apollo</hi> anſwered to <hi>Pindar,</hi> being queſtioned what thing he did
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:153299:39"/>eſteem the moſt healthful and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Man. To die, anſwered he. It is ſaid of <hi>Cleobis</hi> and <hi>Biton,</hi> that God would recompence them for their pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, and obedience, and reſpect which they had born towards their Mother. Now having given them leave to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand what they would, they refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red themſelves to his Judgment, as knowing beſt what is moſt profitable and neceſſary for us then our ſelves: What came of it? The ſame day they died. Whereby did appear that there is nothing more profitable unto man, than Death, by the which we are led into a place of pleaſure, where we begin to live. In the Old Time the Sepulchres were built in Gardens, which was done not only for to bring into our minds our end, in taking off our Pleaſures and Delights, and by that means to moderate them, but alſo for to inſtruct us, that Death is a Guide to Pleaſure and Paradiſe, and is as a paſſage for to enter into a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:153299:40"/>Orchard; it is the reaſon for the which at <hi>Athens,</hi> when they buried the dead Bodies, they turned their Faces towards the Eaſt, and not to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Weſt, to ſhew that in death our Life and Light begins: Why do we put our Bodies in Sepulchres as in Cheſts, if it be not to ſhew that they are not loſt, but layed up as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Veſſels of the Holy Ghoſt, and that in time they ſhall be taken forth, and ſhall be put into Light, for the Decoration of the Houſe of their Lord. Theſe things conſidered, let us take away all fear and apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Death, let us rejoice and ſing as do the Swans when they are near their Death: Let us ſay with <hi>David, Lord I have been glad when it hath been ſaid unto me, Go to, let us go into the Houſe of our Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It remains now, before we end this preſent Treatiſe, to ſhew how we ſhould behave our ſelves at the death of our Friends, and how to
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:153299:40"/>mittigate the Sorrows, which we conceive for them, which to do we muſt conſider that which followeth.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the unavoidable neceſſity of all Men, the which cannot be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medied neither by Counſel nor any other means, <hi>David</hi> having a regard thereunto, did comfort himſelf after the death of his little Child, for whom he had we pt and prayed ſo much during his Sickneſs, when there was yet ſome hope to impetrate of God, by humble Prayers, that he would reſtore him to Health: but when he ſaw that it was too late, that all Tears were now vain and unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, he left his Mourning and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to rejoice. Jeſus Chriſt ſaith, that every day hath Afflictions enough o it ſelf to trouble us, without heap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on thoſe of others, either of thoſe that are gone, renuing it by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of them; or of thoſe which are to come, anticipating by Fear and Cunjecture. This is an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:153299:41"/>moſt neceſſary, and which we ought all to take, for the reſt and tranquility of our Minds.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we muſt conſider when our Friends die, that it is the Will of God which doth, nor ordaineth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but for the good of his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to thoſe that are loved of God, all things ſucceed and turn to their Profit: If we do not believe that, we are Unbelievers: if we believe it, we ought not to grieve for any thing that befals us; for all is profitable to us. Now there is no great reaſon that we ſhould hide us from our Profit. The Soveraign Wiſdom of God is the Cauſe that there is nothing better done than that which he doth; and his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that there is nothing better: If there be nothing better, nor better done than that which he ordaineth and diſpoſeth; and he diſpoſeth of us and of our Affairs, and generally of all that which happeneth unto us,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:153299:41"/>why do we ſorrow, why do we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire any thing elſe? For we cannot have any thing that is better; why do we complain? For all is well and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be better done.</p>
               <p>We muſt thirdly think, that to dye is a thing general and common to all: We paſs and fly away as doth the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a Brook; and it is an act and ſtature of our God, that we muſt dye all: if then that happen unto us which is common to all, is it not a great Folly and Pride in us, to deſire to be exempt from the common condition, and to wiſh for a Particular? What are we the vvorſe that our Friends are Dead? ſo do thoſe of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours die. <hi>Menander</hi> Writing to a Friend of his to comfort him, alleadg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this reaſon unto him: <hi>Thou ſhouldſt have,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>juſt occaſion to grieve if thy fortune and deſtiny were worſe than other Mens, but if it be alike, why doſt thou complain?</hi> There are more that if we would diligently conſider
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:153299:42"/>and make an entire compariſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us and others, we ſhould find there are an iufinite many worſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuned than we are. And that is true which <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> ſaid, as reporteth <hi>Valerius, That if it were poſſible to aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble all the Miſeries of the World on a heap, and afterwards to part them by equal Portions, there is not he but would rather chuſe his own, than his part of the whole Heap.</hi> Seeing that we are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone loſing our Friends, and that if we will look into it, we ſhall find that there are enough more ill at Eaſe than we: Let us content our ſelves, that ſo it pleaſeth God, and let us not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire Immortal Friends, where we ſee thoſe of others to be but Mortal.</p>
               <p>Again, let us think that it is a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural thing to die, as it is for win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be cold, and ſummer hot. Our bodies (ſaith St. <hi>Paul</hi>) are mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal; then let us not marvel if in win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter there be rain, froſt and ſnow, for the ſeaſon brings it. Let us not mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:153299:42"/>that the night follows the day and that man at night after his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour goeth to ſleep, for all that is natural. Alſo ought not we for the the ſame reaſon to be aſtoniſh'd when a man dyety; no more ſaith St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> then when he is born and commeth into the world, for the one and the other is Ordinary: And want of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering it, is cauſe oftentimes that at the death of our Friend we are ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed, as if it were a thing prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and not accuſtomed. When news was brought to <hi>Anaxagoras,</hi> that his ſon was dead, it moved him not at all, only he ſaid that it was not a new and unuſual thing that a mortal man ſhould die, and that when he begot him, he did not beget him immortal. What made him ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, but that before hand he had foreſeen and often conſidered that it ought ſo to come to paſs, being a natural thing?</p>
               <p>Moreover, we muſt conſider, than
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:153299:43"/>death is a tribute which we owe and are bound to pay unto nature. Thou art duſt and earth, and to earth thou ſhalt return, ſaith God, ſpeaking to man after he had ſinned: Then, when one of our Friends dieth, why are we diſcontented? Becauſe he hath quitted himſelf and payed what he ought? If he had payed his King the tribute and ordinary Tax, we would approve of that as moſt right, and an obedience and duty towards his Prince; and if he hath done as much to nature, what reaſon is there to grieve at it?</p>
               <p>Again, that in it God heareth us, for we ask of God that his Kingdom come, and that his will be done; what do we jeſt with God, asking him that which we would not have, and fear to obtain? and do vex our ſelves, and murmur, inſtead of giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him thanks when he hath granted our requeſts? We ſhew well that we think little on the prayers which we
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:153299:43"/>make: for if we thought upon them, either we would not pray ſo, or elſe in praying, ſo if God grant our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, we would not be ſory for it.</p>
               <p>Again, that when our Friends die we loſe them not; for our Lord whoſe they are both before and after death, is not the God of the dead but of the living. <hi>Cirus</hi> ſpeaking to his friends before his death, to comfort them ſaid; Do not think when I ſhall be dead that I am loſt, or ſhall come to nothing. When we ſow a land, the grains of corn are not loſt, they rot therein, but it is the better to fructifie; ſo are our bodies in the earth, for to revive one day, and to riſe again in incorruption, immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and vertue. When alſo a man goeth along and tedious journey, do we think him loſt? When any one of our friends is at the Court with his Prince, who will not ſuffer him to depart out of his Company, raiſed to honour, and provided of great of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:153299:44"/>are we ſorry for it? Why then are we ſorry for a Friend, whom we know aſſuredly to be in the Houſe of God, in honour and credit, and ſo well at eaſe, that he would not change for all the felicity of this world? Again, that it is a very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt and unſeemly thing in a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful man to grieve ſo immoderately and as if he were deſperate. A Chriſtian ought to have a ſtrength and courage, which ſhould be invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible againſt all adverſities, and even againſt the gates of Hell: He ſhould be like a building grounded upon a firm Rock, that may hold firm a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the ſtormes, waves and winds, and all the inconveniences wherewith he may be aſſayled; he muſt not be ſoft, and yield preſently to Adverſity, melting in Tears, and therein drowning (as <hi>David</hi> ſaid) his Bed. The <hi>Lucians</hi> in time paſt had a Law, by the which it was ordained that whoſoever would weep for the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:153299:44"/>Death of his Friend, ſhould put on Womens Cloaths, to ſhew that it is more anſwering to a cowardly and eſſeminate Heat, than to manly Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage. And as it happens in Mens Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, that when they are tender and delicate, they cannot endure the cold in Winter, nor yet the heat in Summer; ſo may we judge of ſuch Courages, that if they cannot bear Adverſity without Impatience, no more can they proſperity without In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolency.</p>
               <p>We muſt finally conſider, that by the Tears and Complaints which we uſe at death of our Friends, we do not remedy our ſelves, no more than doth the ſick Man his Diſeaſe by his Sighs, but rather doth encreaſe his Miſery. And we may ſay that even as by common Experience, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of Phyſicians, we ſee in Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerick Folks, that the more they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger themſelves their Rage and Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler doth augment: alſo in the mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:153299:45"/>and heavy People, that continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their Tears and Lamentations, their Sorrow doth grow and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. So ſaid an ancient Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher to <hi>Arcinoe,</hi> to comfort her; If ſaid he, thou loveſt Tears, they will love thee reciprocally, and as Friends will always frequent and accompany thee: What then doth this great Mourning profit us, if not to make us more miſerable? I, but will ſome ſay, in excuſing themſelves, it is a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural thing to weep at ſuch an acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent: I agree to it, neither will I condemn a moderate Sorrow. As I certain Man ſaw an ancient Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher weeping for the Death of his Son, and did reprove his incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaney: he anſwered him very well, ſaying, <hi>Good Friend, ſuffer me to be a Man.</hi> We muſt not be like Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians or ſavage Beaſts, without Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, without Affection, without Pity nor Feeling. <hi>I wiſh</hi> ſaith <hi>Pinder, not to be Sick, but if I am, I would
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:153299:45"/>not be without feeling; for it is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſign, when in our Sickneſs we are dull and feel nothing.</hi> Then when in our Mourning we ſhall keep the mean, and ſhall avoid the two Extreams, which St. <hi>Baſil</hi> doth condemn as vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, which is, that we be not <hi>Stoiks,</hi> that is to ſay, without affection, nor ſoft on the other ſide, to ſuffer our ſelves to be won and overcome with ſorrow; I do approve that if we ſhew our ſelves Men in Weeping, let us alſo ſhew that we are Chriſtians furniſhed with Hope in correcting and moderating our Sorrows. Others ſay, I loved them ſo dearly. If thou lovedſt him ſo dearly as thou ſayeſt, ſhew it and rejoice at his happineſs and reſt: I rather believe that which cauſeth in us this great Mourning, is the love which we have of our ſelves, which is the cauſe that we grieve at the loſs of our Friends, not for the reſpect which we have to them, but to our ſelves, being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contens
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:153299:46"/>to be deprived of the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Conſolations which they gave us. Which Jeſus Chriſt ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Diſciples, <hi>Seeing that they grieved that he had told them, that in ſhort time he ſhould be put to Death:</hi> It is not for love of me that you are ſo heavy; for if you loved me you would be glad, for as much as it is my good or happineſs to die. Others ſay, he was ſo honeſt a Man, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is it that God took him, as he did <hi>Enock,</hi> for fear leſt by the Malice and Corruption of this Age, he ſhould change. When the Fruit is ripe muſt it not be gathered, for fear leſt it ſhould rot on the Tree?</p>
               <p>Others ſay be died in the prime of his Age; by ſo much the happier is he: for, as ſaid <hi>Anacharſis, That Ship is happieſt which arriveth firſt at the Port.</hi> Moreover, there is no certain time determined for all Men to die: But as we ſee in Fruit time, ſome are gathered ſooner than the others; ſo
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:153299:46"/>is it amongſt Men. There are ſome alſo that ſay, we muſt honour the Dead, by mourning for them, falling into the ſuperſtition of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who holding his opinion, did hire certain Singers and Muſitians, to ſing pitiful and funeral Songs for the Death of their Friends; which Jeſus Chriſt did reprove in the Houſe of the Prince of the Synagogue: and not without cauſe, for it is not good in praiſe o a Body to mourn for it: Complaints and Tears are rather ſigns of Miſery than any thing elſe. We do not now weep for the holy Martyrs, which yet we ſhould do, if in Tears there did conſiſt any Honour; but we ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour them by a remembrance of them, with bleſſing and thankſgiving, and by Pain and Study we endeavour to follow them. If likewiſe we have a Friend whom we will honour after his Death, it muſt not be with Tears and Lamentations, but rather by an honourable manſion which we are
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:153299:47"/>to make of him and of his Vertues, and by a deſire which we have to imitate and follow his good and lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable courſe of Life.</p>
               <p>It is time to conclude this preſent Treatiſe, and to reſolve on the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent Reaſons; that we muſt nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fear nor fly Death, but rather love and deſire it more than Life, and prefer the day of our Death be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the day of our Birth: for by our Birth we come to Pain and Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and dying, we go to God, and to perpetual reſt. Let us then ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly examine them, and judge of them, that we may take away the fear of the one, and the exceſſive love of the other. God through his holy Spirit give us the Grace to do it. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="discourse">
               <pb facs="tcp:153299:47"/>
               <head>A Clear Declaration Of the RESURRECTION Of the DEAD.</head>
               <p>FOraſmuch as in all times there have been ſome who have mocked at the Reſurrection, and have utterly denied it: <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. It is not without good Cauſe that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth ſo carefully teach
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:153299:48"/>us, that the Dead ſhall riſe again: for even as the Knowledge doth bring unto us a Soveraign Joy and Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and doth give us a Will and Affection to follow unto the end JESUS CHRIST our Head and Spouſe, to be Crowned with him, with that Eternal Beatitude which God hath prepared for his Children. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. So alſo thoſe that are not aſſured of the Reſurrection which is the Foundation of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, are leſs affectionate to follow the Lord, and to give themſelves to Piety and Juſtice. And we muſt not doubt but the wicked, who abandon themſelves to all impiety againſt God and who without remorſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience do exerciſe all ſorts of Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs againſt their Neighbours, they do it ſo much the more freely, as to perſwade themſelves that if they eſcape the Judgment and Puniſhment of Men, they ſhall hear nothing of it after this Life. For ſeeing that to
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:153299:48"/>avoid only the vengeance of the Magiſtrate in this World, they hide as much as they can their iniquities, and give ſuch good Colours to their miſ-deeds as poſſibly they can, that they may not be convicted Wicked; how much more do you think they would be bridled from doing Evil, if they were perſwaded that although their Bodies die, yet their Souls ſhall remain Immortal, and ſhall endure the Judgment of God which it hath deſerved; and that one day their Bodies ſhall riſe again, that both Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Soul may be Eternally tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented in Hell, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. by the Judgement of God ſo horrible and fearful; <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. whereupon we may ſee how neceſſary it is to know that the Dead ſhall riſe again, this Doctrine being the principal upholder of Chriſtian Religion; of which if a Man be not altogether perſwaded all is nothing. And it is impoſſible to perſevere amongſt ſo many Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:153299:49"/>and Afflictions which are dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſent at the ſerving of the Lord: For if the hope of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection were not, we ſhould be the moſt miſerable of the Earth, <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. ſeeing that in this World the Faithful are ordinarily more afflicted than the Infidels; but our Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is the Promiſe of Jeſus Chriſt, that although the World ſhall rejoice for a time, and that we ſhall weep, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. and 73. the time will come that our Head will viſit us, and rejoice our Hearts with a Joy that ſhall never be taken from us.</p>
               <p>Now for to underſtand this Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Faith, we muſt well conſider theſe three Points.</p>
               <p>Firſt, we muſt know whether the Soul now dieth with the Body or no.</p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:153299:49"/>
               <p>Secondly, Whether the Body re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns ſo to the Earth, that it cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſe again.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, If it doth riſe, who is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t doth raiſe it, and in what eſtate it ſhall be when riſen.</p>
               <div type="point">
                  <head>The firſt Point.</head>
                  <p>AS for the firſt Part. The Lord for to declare unto us the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality of Souls, compares Death <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o the Sleep of Man, and ſaith that thoſe that are dead, ſleep: aſſuring us, that even ſo as when the Body doth ſleep, the Soul doth not ſleep, as appears by ſo many Dreams which Men have, that alſo, although the Body ſhall be put into the Sepulcher, as in a place of Sleep: nevertheleſs the Immortal Soul ſhall be gathered
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:153299:50"/>and aſſembled in its place; from whence it ſhall come again at the day of Judgment to put on her Body that therein ſhe may enjoy the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Life, or ſuffer Eternal Puniſhment <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. <hi>Luk.</hi> 8. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaking of the Daughter of <hi>Icairus,</hi> whom the Lord did raiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, ſaith, <hi>That the Spirit did return into her;</hi> ſhewing that it was not dead like the Body, but only that ſhe was gone to the Place, from the which by the Commandment of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt ſhe came again to re-enter into her Body: as alſo that of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> of <hi>Bethleem, Joh.</hi> 11. For ever ſo as the Body doth return to the Earth, from whence it was taken; ſo the Spirit doth return to God, who gave it. The ſame Evangeliſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, that the Soul of <hi>Lazarus</hi> lives in Heaven, and that of the evil Rich Man in Hell. <hi>Luc.</hi> 16. And the Lord dying, to ſhew that the Soul was not ſubject to Death as the Body, did
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:153299:50"/>recommend his Soul to his Father. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. <hi>Act.</hi> 7. Saint <hi>Steven</hi> the firſt Martyr, recommended his to Chriſt. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> deſired to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, and to be with Jeſus; <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. knowing that after his Soul ſhould be delivered out of the Priſon of his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, it ſhould go to the Joy of the Children of god. Unto the Thief it was ſaid, <hi>This Day thou ſhalt be with me in Paradiſe; Luk.</hi> 23. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.6. which cannot be underſtood of the Body, but ſhews that the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Dying, makes the paſſage from Death to Life.</p>
                  <p>The which ought only to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the Soul, ſeeing that the Body muſt firſt be brought to Earth, and that it muſt put off all Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for to riſe at the laſt Day In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible and in Glory. <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. Thus Jeſus Chriſt againſt the Saduces, who denied the Immortality of Souls, ſhews, that foraſmuch as God calls himſelf the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:153299:51"/>
                     <hi>Iſaac</hi> and of <hi>Jacob,</hi> Exod. 3. infallibly the Souls departed do live; for he is not the God of thoſe that are dead in ſuch ſort, that they are no more; but he is the God of thoſe that are, and that live; and doth good to the Poſterity of thoſe that are, and not of thoſe that are not; which cannot be underſtood but of their Souls, ſeeing their Bodies were returned to the Earth. Whereby we ſee that they deceive themſelves greatly, that ſay that their Souls die and vaniſh with the Body where they Sleep; alſo thoſe likewiſe who think that they enter into other Bodies <hi>Mak</hi> 6. <hi>Luk.</hi> 9. Even the <hi>Pagans</hi> by natural Apprehenſions, have believe that the Souls were Immortal; a we ſee that <hi>Euripides</hi> in the Tragedy which he intituled <hi>Hecuba,</hi> doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it, when he brings in <hi>Polixen</hi> ſpeaking to <hi>Hecuba,</hi> and dying, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to her, <hi>What ſhall I ſay to</hi> Hect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>thy Husband, who was dead,</hi> ſhe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:153299:51"/>ſwered her, tell him that I am the moſt wretched in the World: And in that which he entituled, The Supplicant, he ſays, The Spirit ſhall return to Heaven. Likewiſe, <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licides</hi> ſays, That the Soul is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, and living always, wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not old: <hi>Pythagoras</hi> in his Golden Verſes, ſaid, If when thou haſt left the Body thou comeſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Heaven, thou ſhalt be as God, living always, and being no more Mortal: <hi>Cicero</hi> likewiſe Writes of it in his Book of Friendſhip, and in that which he writ of Age, in ſome ſort comforting himſelf in the hope which he had of the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality of his Soul. We ſee then that it is a thing moſt aſſured, that the Soul is immortal, as the Lord by his Word, which is the Infallible Truth of Heaven, doth ſhew it us: And likewiſe, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, how Ignorant ſoever they were of the true Religion, have
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:153299:52"/>well underſtood it. Wherefore thoſe that deny the Immortality of Souls, accuſe God of lying, and make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in worſe eſtate than the Pagans.</p>
                  <p>This Knowledge is a great Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the Faithful in all their Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, and doth take from them the fears of Death, knowing that their Souls being ſeparated from their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies live in Heaven, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2 in which they are admoniſhed, not to ſettle themſelves upon the tranſitory things of this Life; and not to load their Souls with the burthen of Sin, to the end that dying they may be raiſed up towards God our Father, and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Saviour, unto whom we ought with a ſtedfaſt faith to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend them. Now even as the faithful do rejoice at it, the unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful on the other ſide, knowing the Souls to be immortal, are ſo much the more fearful of Death; ſeeing the eternal pains, and torments to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:153299:52"/>for them at their going forth of this World. <hi>James</hi> 1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. So that which ſerveth to the Elect for Joy and Inſtruction, is unto the wicked nothing but Sorrow, and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of Deſpair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="point">
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:153299:53"/>
                  <head>The Second Point.</head>
                  <p>TOuching the Body, it is all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant that it is ſubject to die, as well becauſe that we know that thoſe that were in times paſt are dead, and that we ſee that thoſe of our time die one after another; as prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally becauſe that the Lord declares to <hi>Adam,</hi> that by reaſon of his Sin, he with his poſterity ſhall be ſubject to return into the Earth, from whence he was taken. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. The Apoſtle ſays, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8.6. That by Man Sin
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:153299:53"/>came into the World, and by Sin Death, and ſo Death came unto all Men, by reaſon that all have ſinned, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd the reward of Sin is Death, whereof the hour is uncertain unto us. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uke</hi> 12. Although we are certain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat it is the Journey that every man muſt go, by reaſon that unto them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll it is ordained to die once. <hi>Joſ.</hi> 12. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2: The Scripture is full of Teſtimonies upon this matter, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be well enough known of all by every days Experience. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. <hi>Job</hi> 14. The <hi>Pagans</hi> themſelves with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Inſtruction of the Word of God, have well underſtood that unto Man it is a thing that cannot be avoided; as <hi>Euripedes</hi> ſhews it in the Tragedie of the Supplicants, ſaying, <hi>That eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part of Man muſt return from whence it came; the Spirit into Heaven, the Body into the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ih, which is the Mother and Nurſe thereof. Wherefore it is a thing known to all, that we muſt
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:153299:54"/>die;</hi> but now by how much it is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to believe, that neceſſity to die is impoſed upon us, by ſo much is i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> more difficult to believe that our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies being returned to duſt, ſhall riſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> again: And indeed the ſenſual Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> cannot comprehend any thing there in, neither hath any thought of it; as we ſee that the <hi>Pagans</hi> never thought of it, although that they have diſputed of the immortality o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Souls. But the Man that is regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate by the Spirit of God, doubt not but that the Lord can raiſe the dead, ſeeing he will have it ſo, and that nothing can hinder his Will <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115. For as, ſayth the Prophet he doth what he will. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 4. We muſt then fee how the Scripture dot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> aſſure us, that the Bodies as well o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the good as of the wicked, ſhall riſe again, the firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o be crowned with Glory, the other with perpetual In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. For to teach us th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:153299:54"/>Reſurrection, it compares Death to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>leep, as hath been already ſaid, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he end we may be certain that as the bodies, after they have laboured ſhall reſt by Sleep, that they being awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked may with ſo much more alacrity return to work; ſo when we ſhall have made an end of this preſent Life, our Bodies ſhall be brought to the Tomb, as in a Bed of reſt, for to riſe again from thence at the latter day, and be put into their place. <hi>Job.</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecying of the Reſurrection, the which he did firmly believe, ſays, <hi>I know that my Redeemer liveth, and that he will ſtand up at the latter day upon the Earth, and although after my Skin, this Body ſhall be devoured by Worms, yet with my Fleſh ſhall I ſee God, I ſhall behold him, and my Eyes ſhall look upon him, and none other for me, although my Reins are conſumed within me.</hi> Job. 14. &amp; 19. <hi>David</hi> foretels the Reſurrection of Chriſt, by whom we ſhall riſe again; the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:153299:55"/>which was figured by this, that <hi>Jonas</hi> was three days and three nights in the Whales Belly, as Jeſus Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf declares it. <hi>Johu</hi> 2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. The Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> in the 26. <hi>Chap.</hi> ſpeaking of the Elect, ſaith unto the Lord with Faith, Thy dead ſhall live and riſe again with my Body. Awake and rejoice ye Inhabitants of the duſt, for thy dew is as the dew of the Fields, and the Earth ſhall caſt forth the dead. The Lord willing to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure his People <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that delivering them from the Captivity of <hi>Babylon,</hi> he would bring them back into the Land which he had given them, he ſaid unto them in a Viſion, by the Prophet, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37. that as certain as the dead ſhall riſe, ſo certainly will he deliver them from the Captivity of the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> for to ſet them in Peace in their own Land. <hi>Danie</hi> ſaith, that thoſe that ſleep in the duſt ſhall wake, ſome to Eternal Life, and others to perpetual ſhame
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:153299:55"/>and Infamy, and thoſe which have been wiſe, ſhall ſhine as the Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Firmament, and thoſe which do perſwade Man to Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, ſhall be as Stars for ever and ever. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. Jeſus Chriſt ſhews the <hi>Saduces,</hi> that the dead ſhall riſe again, becauſe that God is their God, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. In St. <hi>John, Chap.</hi> 6. he ſaith, that the will of his Father who ſent him, is, that he ſhall loſe nothing of all that he hath given him; but that he ſhall raiſe it up at the larter day. The Apoſtle declares that Chriſt is riſen again for our Juſtification. Then he ſaith that even as we die in <hi>Adam,</hi> ſo we ſhall riſe again, and ſhall be quickened in Chriſt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5.6. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. For ſeeing that he who is the Life, when he was put into the Tomb, thereby made many to riſe again, by much more reaſon now, being riſen again and glorified, will he raiſe us again. <hi>John</hi> 19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36. <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. In like manner he declares,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:153299:56"/>That he that believes Jeſus is dead, and riſen again (of which we have the ſureſt Teſtimonies) ought by the ſame parity of Reaſon to believe, that God will bring from the Grave thoſe that ſleep in Jeſus, who ſhall from thence forth ever live with the Lord, wherefore, ſays St. <hi>Paul,</hi> comfort one another with theſe Words, that is, let this be your Conſolation in the midſt of all your Trials, Afflictions, and Troubles up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth, that they cannor laſt long, but muſt end with your Life; when you ſhall deſcend into the Grave, where you ſhall not long remain, but the ſame Power that raiſed your Bleſſed Redeemer from thence, ſhall have the ſame effect on you, and likewiſe raiſe you from the Dead, and you ſhall be joined with Chriſt your Head, and live with him in everlaſting Glory; this is the very ſum of our Chriſtian Profeſſion, and the higheſt point of our Faith.</p>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:153299:56"/>
                  <p>All humane wiſdom, which is fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before God, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.25. cannot perſwade themſelves, that the bodies which are returned into duſt can riſe again, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>Phil.</hi> 7. nor thoſe which have been burned, whereof the aſhes have been diſperſed with the winds, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.4. nor thoſe which have been devoured by birds and by beaſts, and dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, and reduced to dung, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1. nor thoſe which have periſhed in the waters, which have been food for fiſhes, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. But the Lord by that which he had done before, plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſheweth, that hereafter it ſhall be very eaſie for him to do what he will with our bodies; for ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he hath made all things of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, can he not make that to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to life, which hath already been? <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. And as he made man firſt of the Earth, can he not as well make
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:153299:57"/>him to riſe again from it? <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. in the beginning the Earth was ſo obedient unto him, that when he commanded it to bring forth the bud of the herbs that beareth ſeed, and the fructifying tree, and the living creature, beaſts, worms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It of it ſelf, immediately brings forth that which before had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been; how much more eaſily by the commandment of God, may it reſtore many which have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy been, and ſhall be returned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it? <hi>John</hi> 11. We ſee that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that <hi>Lazarus</hi> of <hi>Bethania,</hi> had already been three days in the Earth, and nevertheleſs when the Lord commanded him to come out of the Earth, preſently it was done; He himſelf alſo roſe again from the Earth the third day, for to aſſure us that he will raiſe us again, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1. for as death could not overcome Jeſus Chriſt, but that he is riſen, ſo ſhall it not be
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:153299:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>able to hinder his members from riſing again, becauſe that he hath as much power over the dead, as over the living; <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.4. If God hath raiſed the head, it followeth, that he will alſo raiſe the body, which we are if we believe, When we conſider that he did hinder the ſo hot bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning furnace from doing any hurt to <hi>Sidrake, Miſake,</hi> and <hi>Abednego, Eph.</hi> 4. <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. we ſhall not find it an impoſſible thing to God, to make them riſe again which have been buried, that they may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>united unto their Souls. And he that ſhut the Lyons Jaws, becauſe they ſhould do no harm to <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, Dan.</hi> 6. ſhall be able to raiſe thoſe again which have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured, And he commanded the fiſh to caſt up <hi>Jonas, Jon.</hi> 2. alſo can be eaſily cauſe that the Sea ſhall obey him, when he ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:153299:58"/>it to caſt up his dead. In brief, the faithful cannot doubt of his Reſurrection, knowing that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Death, nor Life, nor Angels, nor Principalities, nor powers, nor things preſent, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature, can ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate him from the love which God beareth in him, in Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, <hi>Revel.</hi> 20. For alſo the Sea muſt caſt up thoſe dead bodies which are in it, and death and the Grave, thoſe which are in them; for as much as the Lord hath the keys of the Grave and of death, having power over them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. Moreover God cannot be true, nor truly wiſe, nor Almighty, nor Juſt, if he doth not raiſe the dead, and by conſequence cannot be God. And ſo who denyeth the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, denyeth alſo that there is a God: for ſeeing by his Word he promiſeth to raiſe up the dead, if he do it not,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:153299:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>he is not true. And ſeeing that he declares that he will have it, if he doth it not, it follows, that it is for want of knowledge, and of power, and ſo ſhall neither be truly wiſe nor Almighty. Alſo he ſhall not be juſt if he doth not render to every one that which he promiſeth him; for the Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſaying that God is, ſaith alſo that he is a rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of thoſe that ſeek him. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. <hi>Marc.</hi> 8. <hi>Luc.</hi> 9, Now in this world, the children of God have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but afflictions every day, being ſet out for a ſhew, as men condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to death, and being made a ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle to the world, to the Angels and to men. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. <hi>John</hi> 16. As our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour alſo ſaith to his diſciples, You ſhall weep and lament, and the world ſhall rejoyce, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. And the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle declares, that whoſoever will live holy in Chriſt, he ſhall endure affliction. <hi>Act.</hi> 5.20. 21. We ſee that the Apoſtles and thoſe which received
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:153299:59"/>their doctrine, have almoſt always been in continual afflictions. <hi>Col.</hi> 1. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.11. In our time the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the faithful have been notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that there is none ſo ſimple but may ſee them. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. <hi>Marc.</hi> 14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10, 11. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.3. On the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part the wicked inſtead of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving puniſhment in this world, are ordinarily better at their eaſe than the faithful, and do flouriſh like the bay Tree, as ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. Wherefore there muſt neceſſarily be another place where the good ſhall be recompenced with joy, and the wicked with ſorrow, otherwiſe God ſhould not be juſt, and Chriſt ſhould have dyed in vain. But ſome one will ſay, God doth accompliſh his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes upon the ſouls of the juſt, and his threatnings upon thoſe of the unjuſt, and by that means God ſhall not ceaſe to be juſt, although he ſhould not raiſe again the bodies of men. With this we muſt conſider, that if it be ſo,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:153299:59"/>that a free retribution is done to the ſoul, as (according to the promiſe of God) it ought to be done to the juſt, and puniſhment is juſtly inflicted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſoul of the reprobate, to the end that the juſtice of God may be ſafe; ſo muſt it alſo of neceſſity be, that the bodies be recompenced, ſome with honour, others with diſdain, to the end that God may remain juſt for ever. For even as the Soul of man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued by the holy Ghoſt, giveth it ſelf to ſerve God, ſo doth the body, when it ceaſeth from evil doing, and being even ready to be martyr'd for profeſſing the Lord, ſerving to Juſtice and Holineſs. <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. For Example we have the Prophets, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. <hi>Act.</hi> 7. St, <hi>Stephen,</hi> the Apoſtles, and ſo many Martyrs, and true Servants of God, whoſe bodies have greatly given them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſerve God; <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.8. Alſo in like manner as the ſpirit of the wicked doth imploy it ſelf but only to offend God, likewiſe they employ
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:153299:60"/>their bodies to ſerve to filthineſs and iniquity, and to do all evil; <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.7. therefore juſt it is that the bodies of the Saints which ſerved God, and of the wicked which diſobeyed God, ſhould both be raiſed by him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive according to what they have done for or againſt him. Furthermore they who deny the Reſurrection of the body, do likewiſe make the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation and bodily paſſion of Jeſus Chriſt unprofitable. For if the body do not riſe again, what needed he to take humane nature upon him, and to ſuffer in it, to deliver our bodies from the everlaſting curſe? Seeing that if it were ſo, that the bodies being dead, ſhould ſo return to the Earth, that they ſhould have no more being, and ſo could neither enjoy happineſs, nor ſuffer pains and ſorrows; had it not been enough that he had only ſuffered his ſoul, being heavy to death, for to deliver the Souls from Hell? <hi>Marc.</hi> 14. Whoſoever then denies
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:153299:60"/>the re-eſtabliſhment of bodies, thro' ignorance makes the humanity of Chriſt unprofitable, and accuſeth God the Father of cruelty, as if he had taken pleaſure to ſee his well beloved Son ſo cruelly entreated, without having (for his part) deſerved it, and without that it ſhould ſerve to the Elect; he maketh him alſo (for his part) in blaſpheming, a Lyer with his Father, becauſe he ſays, that he will raiſe his at the laſt day. In like manner doth he accuſe the holy Ghoſt of vanity, which by the mouth of the Prophets hath propheſied and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told the Reſurrection of the Dead. Alſo he diſanulleth Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for if the dead do not riſe again, Chriſt alſo is not riſen, and ſo the preaching of the Apoſtles ſhould be falſe, and we ſhould be abuſed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve their doctrine, and thoſe which are dead in Chriſt ſhould be caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. The Lord fitting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to our capacity, as the mother to
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:153299:61"/>the child, teacheth us the Coeleſtial things by the compariſon of the things Terreſtrial, to the end we comprehend that which otherwiſe is incomprehenſible unto us. And touching the matter which we have now in hand, the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares unto us, <hi>Eſai.</hi> 19. that even as in Winter the graſs of the field ſeems to be dead, and in the ſpring after it hath felt the dew it ſprings and waxeth green again, ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe our bodies being dead ſhall riſe again, when at the latter day they ſhall feel the dew of the grace of God, hearing the voice of the Son of man. The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. that as the ſeed muſt die before it be quickned, 1 <hi>Theſſ. John</hi> 5. and then it riſeth by vertue of the ſap which it hath had in the Earth, in great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er glory then it was ſown; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. ſo likewiſe all men muſt die, that they may riſe again, the elect in greater glory then they were
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:153299:61"/>ſet upon the Earth, by the vertue of the eternal Spirit of Jeſus, in whom they died; <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. the probate in greater diſhonour then they were before, by the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the immortal ſpirit of Satan, in whom they are departed. For ſeeing the Lord doth excellently unfold his power towards the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible creatures, we ought not to doubt, but he hath at the leaſt as much will to ſhew his power in making them to riſe again for whom he died, to the end to crown them with glory; and his enemies to be charged with ſhame and infamy, ſeeing they have ſo much diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured him. When a nut, or the kernel of a Pear or Apple is rotted in the ground, God cauſeth it to riſe again to a great tree, for to bear much more fruit, being riſen again, then it did before; and a grane of Wheat, being put into the ground, and dying, brings forth
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:153299:62"/>much fruit; <hi>John</hi> 12. do we think that the Lord hath not as great power to raiſe up men, as he hath to raiſe theſe things, ſo ſmall; and as it were of no value? Shall it not be eaſie for him to raiſe us again, as it hath been eaſie to him to draw us forth of the matrix of the mother alive, where before we were born, we were as it were in a Sepulchre? If the Prophets and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles in the name of God have raiſed up the dead, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18, ſhall it be impoſſible to the Lord by his power to raiſe them? 2 <hi>King</hi> 4. <hi>Acts</hi> 9. Let us aſſure our ſelves, that nothing can ſeparate the body and ſoul of the faithful from the love which God beareth them, neither hinder, but that he ſhall make the wicked both in body and ſoul to be his foot-ſtool.</p>
                  <p>Now by reaſon that the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>John</hi> 6. that the body which
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:153299:62"/>is ſown is not that which riſeth again; <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. there are ſome that will infer thereupon, that at the Reſurrection our ſouls ſhall not return into thoſe bodies which now we have, but into other bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies which the Lord ſhall give us. He himſelf in that place ſheweth us, that he ſpeaks not that, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſhew us, that although our bodies ſhall riſe in the ſame ſubſtance which now they have, they ſhall notwithſtanding be changed in qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and glory; ſeeing that this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption moſt put on incorruption, and that this mortality ſhall be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up of life, and put on im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. declaring that they ſhall be theſe ſelf ſame bodies in ſubſtance, but divers in qualities. St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. Chriſt will transform this vile body, that it may be made like unto his glorious bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y, according to the power by which he is able to make all things
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:153299:63"/>ſubject unto himſelf. <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. Whereon followeth, that as Jeſus Chriſt roſe again in the ſame body, which was crucified for us, being cleanſed and diſcharged of all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity; <hi>Luke</hi> 24. <hi>John</hi> 20. alſo we ſhall riſe again in the ſame bodies which now we have in this world, having in them, cold, heat, hunger and thriſt, poverty, ſickneſs, baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, impriſonment, and ſuch like adverſities: <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 11. being cleanſed and diſrobed of all that which by ſin did cauſe us any grief; for Juſtice of God cannot conſiſt without remunerating the bodies of thoſe that have ſought for his glory, in crowning his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in them, and puniſhing thoſe which have laboured to offend him. Moreover we ſee that thoſe which the Prophets and Apoſtles, and Jeſus Chriſt himſelf have raiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. it hath been in the ſelf ſame bodies in the which the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:153299:63"/>had lived before. Who doubts but thoſe that roſe again at the death of our Lord, did riſe in the ſelf ſame hodies which they had before; for otherwiſe how ſhould they have been known by thoſe to whom they did appear? The Apoſtles puts us out of doubt of it, ſaying, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. That if the Spirit of him who raiſed Jeſus from the dead, doth dwell in us, he that hath raiſed up Chriſt from the dead, will alſo quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en our mortal bodies, becauſe his ſpirit dwelleth in us; he ſaith more over, that the body which is ſown in corruption, ſhall riſe again in incorruption. It is ſown in diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, it ſhall riſe again in glory; it is ſown in weakneſs, it ſhall riſe again in power: it is ſown a ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al body, it ſhall riſe a ſpiritual bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. Wherefore we ought to believe that the bodies which now we have, ſhall be the ſelf ſame which ſhall riſe again in the ſame ſubſtance, but
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:153299:64"/>the earthly qualities ſhall be changed into heavenly; which is no ſmall conſolation, ſeeing that we love our bodies ſo much, although that in this world they be laden with ſo many miſeries.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="point">
                  <head>The Third point.</head>
                  <p>AS concerning the Authour of the Reſurrection, the Scripture doth declare unto us, that God the Father in the beginning made man by his word. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 2. which is his ſon, <hi>John</hi> 1. and having made his body, breathed into him a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſoul, by his ſpirit; <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33. ſo in the Reſurrection of the dead, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. he ſhall raiſe us again by his Son in a quickning ſpirit.</p>
                  <p>And when the Son of juſtice ſhall come in judgment for to judge the quick and the dead, <hi>Mal.</hi> 4. the Sun ſhall wax dark, <hi>Revel.</hi> 1. and
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:153299:64"/>the Moon ſhall not yield her light, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. and the brightneſs of the Stars ſhall be ſeen no more then if they were fallen from Heaven, and the vertues which are in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, as the Stars, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, and other coeleſtial creatures, with Heaven and Earth ſhall be ſhaken; <hi>Luke</hi> 21. <hi>Revel.</hi> 6. then the Sea and her waves ſhall roar after an unaccuſtomed manner; 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. and when the order of nature ſhall be changed, thoſe ſhall be ſigns of the coming of the Son of man. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. And when that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, the Son of God ſhall come, who took humane nature up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him in the Virgins womb, <hi>Luke</hi> 1. <hi>Acts</hi> 1. he ſhall come in the ſame body, wherewith he did converſe here below upon the Earth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and after his death, as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf declares, calling himſelf the Son of man, ſent of God his Father, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. <hi>Mark</hi> 13. (who gave him
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:153299:65"/>power to do judgment, in ſo much as he is the Son of man) <hi>Luke</hi> 24. <hi>John</hi> 5. ſet above the clouds, at the right hand of the power of God, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.24. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with the voices of Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angels, and of Angels with Gods Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. and all eyes ſhall behold him; <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. for he will cauſe his ſign to appear in Heaven, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. and his voice to be heard, the which at the laſt trump ſhall be heard of thoſe that have been put into the Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chres, to the end that firſt they may riſe again: 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. and thoſe which ſhall be found living ſhall hear it alſo, to the end they may be tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated, which unto them ſhall be a kind of death, being changed from mortal and corruptible, to immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall and incorruptible bodies, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 35. and ſhall riſe again, and ſhall be changed in a moment and twinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of an eye.</p>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:153299:65"/>
                  <p>This day ſhall not ſurpriſe the elect that are in the light, becauſe it ſhall be the day which they have ſo long waited for, and wiſhed, with the other creatures, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1, for to thoſe who have overcome Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan by the blood of the Lamb, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. and by the word of their teſtimony, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. and have not loved their lives to death, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.4.8.5. it ſhall bring unto them an unſpeakable joy, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.21. making them lift up their heads aloft, ſeeing their perfect delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance come. For their Saviour ſhall ſend his Angels with great ſound of Trumpets, to gather them together, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 35. how far in ſunder ſoever they be from the four winds, <hi>Zach.</hi> 9. from the end of the earth to the end of heaven, <hi>Luc.</hi> 22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. and then they ſhall be altogether caught with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the clouds to meet the Lord in the Air, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. for to be joyned with their head, as members of his body, and ſhall be always with him who
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:153299:66"/>will ſeparate them from the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, as the Shepheard doth the Sheep from the Goates, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. to put them both in body and ſoul in full poſſeſſion of the everlaſting heritage and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs by them ſo long hoped for.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Eſtate of the Elect that are Riſen again.</head>
                  <p>THen their bodies which ſhall be riſen again in triumph ſhall be changed, not in ſubſtance but in qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, being diſcharged of the earthly heavineſs, for to be made ſpiritual bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. to the end to be fit for the heavenly habitation; where they have no need of meats which do corrupt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7. for they ſhall be no more hungry, nor thirſty, and they ſhall dye no more, but ſhall uſe the heavenly food, which is the word of God, <hi>Luc.</hi> 20. they ſhall alſo be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from the bondage of ſin, for to ſerve evermore to Juſtice. For theſe
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:153299:66"/>are the two principal things which hinder man from beholding the face of God, this heavy earthly body, and infectious ſin. And for the firſt, we ſee that the Lord ſaid to <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 33. who was deſirous to ſee him; Man ſhall not ſee me upon the Earth and live. As for the other, it was cauſe that the wicked Angels were caſt down from Heaven, and man out of Paradice, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. for there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing common between God and a ſinful man. Wherefore the faithful ſhall have a ſpiritual body, diſcharged and purified from all ſin. There ſhall alſo be no defect in their bodies, nor imperfection, and all deformity and vice, which cometh of ſin, ſhall be done away; for the Lord will tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form their vile and contemptible bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and make them conformable and like unto his glorious body. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. Moreover, they ſhall no more ſuffer any torments, pains, ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, nor any other adverſe thing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:153299:67"/>there ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>rn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor weeping nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>uring; for the Lord will wipe away all tears from their Eyes. And there ſhall happen no more corruption to them by death, <hi>Rev.</hi> 25. whereof there ſhall be no more remembrance, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25. but being made immortal, they ſhall be made incorruptible, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.21. and delivered from all ſuffering, for to be in a happy ſtate for ever.</p>
                  <p>Their Soul, which before was a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Soul, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. ſhall be changed into a quickning ſpirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. then it ſhall be delivered from all ſorrows, griefs, annoy, perturbations and fear, which came thro' ſin, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 61. and ſhall be ſet in reſt, joy, conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, happineſs, and perpetual aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, without being any more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed nor defiled with troubleſom affections.</p>
                  <p>Then being put in ſo excellent eſtate, both of Body and Soul, the Image of God ſhall truly ſhine upon
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:153299:67"/>them, having this power to ſerve God, being perfectly wiſe, holy, pure, ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reprehenſible, innocent, without ſpot, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. good, juſt, true, immortal and incorruptible, being reſplendant in glory and honour, before the Throne of God <hi>Col.</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p>The which ſhall be the white veſture, wherewith St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.21. They ſhall be cloathed, which is the pure and ſhining Veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.4.6.7. which are the juſtifications of the Saints that ſhall hold the Palms in their hands in ſign of Victory, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. after that the books being opened, they ſhall hear the Voice full of meekneſs, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7. grace and mercy, receiving in the preſence of the wicked, who judged them the out-caſts of the Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10. the ſentence of eternal bleſſing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing found written in the book of life, which is the book of the Lamb, <hi>Sap.</hi> 4.5. being clothed with the innocency of Jeſus Chriſt: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:153299:68"/>and having the name of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther written in their forehead, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.21. they ſhall be with Chriſt the Spouſe, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. crowned with the incorruptible crown of life, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. and eternal glory, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 14. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pronounced the ſons and heirs of God, and co-heirs with Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. and Judges with him of the Apoſtate Angels, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. and of the reprobate, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. for all power and judgment is ſo given to the Son. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. that he will participate in this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour as his aſſiſtants, <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 3. they ſhall be put in poſſeſſion of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. having praiſe of God, <hi>Luc.</hi> 22. which is the incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible heritage, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. which cannot contaminate, nor wither, and which is preſerved in Heaven for them, <hi>John</hi> 5. they ſhall ſhine therein as the Firmament, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. and as the Sun, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. and as the Stars for ever. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. Then they ſhall have
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:153299:68"/>their right in the Tree of Life, <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. and ſhall enter into the new Coeleſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al <hi>Jeruſalem, Dan.</hi> 12. in the which there ſhall be no Temple, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. for the Lord Almighty is the Temple thereof, and the Lamb, <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 3. They ſhall be in it everlaſting Kings and High Prieſts, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.21, 22. offering ſacrifices of Praiſe and Thankſgiving unto the Lord. Then being in the Houſe of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.7. which is the bleſſed houſe which the faithful have in Heaven, which is not made with hands, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. they ſhall be filled with the magnificence of the Lord, and ſhall bud like the Olive branch, and bloſſom like the Palm, and like the Cedar which is in <hi>Leba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Pſal.</hi> 16.17.52. &amp; 92. being immortal and incorruptible, and ſhall not be importuned by Satan, to ſin and offend God. The face of God which is the Fountain of Light, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. the River of Pleaſure, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. and Ocean of Goodneſs, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. they
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:153299:69"/>ſhall ſee, which ſhall give them ſuch a great and perfect Joy, that all the Joys which may be compared to that, are but as a ſparkle compared to a great Fire, <hi>Marc.</hi> 9. It will make them forget all Terreſtrial, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.12. what pleaſure ſoever they could take in them in the world, and they ſhall not remember any thing that may bring them ſorrow or grief. They ſhall be led to the Mountain of <hi>Sion,</hi> and to the City of the living God, (which hath no need of the Sun nor Moon to ſhine in it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.22. for the light of God hath lightned it, and the Lamb is the Candle thereof) and of thouſands of Angels, and of the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of the firſt born, which are written in Heaven, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. and to God which is the Judge of all, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. and to the ſanctified Souls of the Juſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. and to Jeſus Chriſt their Head and their Spouſe, Mediator of the new Covenant, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. and of the blood ſhed, ſpeaking better things
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:153299:69"/>then that of <hi>Abel:</hi> then with all his company, and the other Saints, with whom they ſhall be fellow Citizens, being domeſticks of God; they ſhall be called to the nuptial banquet of the Lamb, and ſhall enjoy the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God their Father, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. the felicity which Jeſus Chriſt by his death hath conquered for them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5.9.10. in whom they have put their whole truſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.4. as he himſelf promiſeth, ſaying, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5. Father, I will that thoſe which thou haſt given me be with me, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.5. and ſee my glory which thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.9.10. and then I diſpoſe the Kingdom unto you, as the Father hath diſpoſed it unto me <hi>John</hi> 12.14.17. to the end that you may eat upon my Table in my Kingdom. The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Luc.</hi> 22. If we dye with him we ſhall live with him; and if we ſuffer with him we ſhall reign with him, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. and ſhall be glorified with him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. Of
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:153299:70"/>theſe promiſes the Children of God need not doubt; for ſeeing that the Lord when he died, gave Paradiſe to the Thief, can be not more eaſily give it to thoſe to whom he hath promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, <hi>Luc.</hi> 23. when he ſhall come into ſuch great Glory and Majeſty? And now being with him, and ſeeing him as he is, they ſhall have a much greater Joy then had the Diſciples, ſeeing him transfigured; that ſhall be ſo underſtanding, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17. that they ſhall know all the Saints that ever have been, <hi>Marc.</hi> 9. <hi>Luc.</hi> 9. and even thoſe with whom they have converſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this world joyfully, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to God. For if it be ſo that in the transfiguration of our Lord, which was but a little demonſtration, as well of the Glory of the Body of Jeſus, as of the eſtate and condition in the which the Children of God ſhall be in Heaven, (for their mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and infirmity could not have been able to ſee the incomprehenſible Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:153299:70"/>of the Lord, without being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed) The Apoſtles, although they had never ſeen the body of <hi>Elias</hi> and of <hi>Moſes,</hi> nevertheleſs they knew them. How much ſooner ſhall the Elect know one another, when they ſhall be endued with this perfect knowledge and intelligence of the Image of God, which ſhall be in them? And if <hi>Adam</hi> in his firſt eſtate, which was a great deal leſs glorious then that of the ſanctified by Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. did know the beaſts which God brought before him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. and did properly impoſe a Name to each one: and even knewn <hi>Eve</hi> to be bone of his bones, and fleſh of his Fleſh; although that the Lord took the rib from him without his feeling it; ſhall not we in this admirable glory have more wiſdom to know each other? <hi>Luc.</hi> 16. Now this knowledge ſhall be diſrobed of all carnal and corrupt affection; for the Elect ſhall not be known for loving
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:153299:71"/>the one more then the other, or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one reprobate more then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or in calling to mind the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and diſpleaſures which they may have received in this world.</p>
                  <p>But they ſhall love directly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect of perſons, thoſe which God loveth, and ſhall hold in abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination thoſe which God ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt; For then all Paternity, brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and Mariage ſhall be aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and there ſhall be but God alone Father of all, whoſe Children we ſhall be, and Brothers and Siſters one to another: the Children of God ſhall be made Partakers of the divine Nature, <hi>Marc.</hi> 12. for God ſhall be glorified in his Saints, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. and ſhall be made admirable to thoſe that have believed. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. Wherefore ſeeing God will commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate his Glory, Vertue and Juſtice to his Elect, imparting himſelf unto them; let us know, that this benefit contains the ſoveraign good of man,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:153299:71"/>which all deſire, and which the wiſdom of man could never com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend. And indeed when by all the ſimilitudes which the Scripture doth teach us, we ſhall have ſaid and learned much of the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the children of God, it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt nothing in compariſon of that which ſhall then appear; ſurely then the Apoſtle with the Prophet hath good reaſon, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. having taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſpirit the ineſtimable glory of the Elect in the heavenly life, to ſay, the things which Eye hath not ſeen, nor Ear heard, and which is not come into the heart of man, are thoſe which God hath prepared for them which loveth him, which are unſpeakable: and it is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for man to tell them. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. For although <hi>Adam</hi> was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in a very noble eſtate, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 64. yet ſo it is, that if the Elect were to re-aſſume that eſtate, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. they ſhould be miſerable in regard
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:153299:72"/>of the ſoveraign excellency, in the which they ſhall be ſet.</p>
                  <p>For, Firſt, he had an earthly and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual body, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. the Elect ſhall have Spiritual and Coeleſtial bodies, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He had a living ſoul, they ſhall have a quickning ſpirit.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He could fail and render him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſubject to death, they ſhall not be able to fail, nor fall in danger of death; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. the which then ſhall be aboliſhed.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Satan</hi> had power both to tempt him, and to make him to fall; but he ſhall not have power of either to them.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. He was huſbanding in an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Paradiſe, they ſhall be in reſt and enjoy the Heavenly Paradiſe.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. He had command over the birds of the Air, the fiſhes of the Sea, the beaſts of the Earth; <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. they being in greater power ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn <hi>Satan</hi> and all the wicked:
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:153299:72"/>and the holy Angels ſhall be their companions, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. and ſhall have power in the Kingdom of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. <hi>Adam</hi> had ſuch great wiſdom, that he named every beaſt accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their property; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. they ſhall be endued with ſuch wiſdom, all filled with ſuch a perfect know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.3.5. that they ſhall be ignorant of nothing. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3, Surely then we ought to be much moved and ſtirred up to worſhip and ſerve God; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. who, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any deſert of ours, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.4. will for the love of his well-beloved Son ſo admirably un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold his incomprehenſible goodneſs unto us, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.17.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Eſtate of the reprobate.</head>
                  <p>NOW this day ſhall ſurprize the wicked and reprobates which are in darkneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.2.
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:153299:73"/>(whom the Lord hath borne and ſuffered with great patience, to the end to bring them to repentance) as the Thief by night ſtealeth upon the Maſter of the family while he ſleepeth: and they ſhall be found without cloaths, and ſhall walk na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. and their ſhame ſhall be ſeen: <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. for when they ſhall ſay peace and ſecurity, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. then ſhall ſudden deſtruction come upon them, like to a woman in tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. and they ſhall not eſcape, but ſhall be marvelouſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, by reaſon that it ſhall be a day of darkneſs unto them, <hi>Amos</hi> 5. and not of light, an obſcure and not a clear day, and then they ſhall be condemned by their own conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, like unto <hi>Cain,</hi> giving praiſe to God, ſeeing the Lord with his Saints come, which are by millions, for to give judgment againſt thoſe that have not had the fear of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eyes: and to the end to
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:153299:73"/>convince all the wicked of all the evil works which they have wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly done, <hi>Sap.</hi> 4.5. and of the rude ſpeeches which the wicked have preferred againſt him: <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. then for to weigh down the Wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs of the anger and wrath of Almighty God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. becauſe they have perſecuted Jeſus Chriſt in his members, <hi>Jude. Rom.</hi> 3. which are bones of his bones, and fleſh of his fleſh; <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. ſo that they ſhall be in ſuch great Agonies and Afflictions, feeling the terrible judgment of God to come upon them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. that they ſhall hide themſelves in holes and between the ſtones of the Mountains, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. and ſhall ſay to the Mountains and ſtones, fall upon us, and hide us from the Face of him who is ſet upon the throne, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. and from the wrath of the Lamb; <hi>Rev.</hi> 9. for the great day of his wrath is come, and who is it ſhall be able
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:153299:74"/>to ſubſiſt; They ſhall ſeek for Death and not find it, and ſhall deſire to die, but Death ſhall fly from them; they ſhall ſtrike themſelves with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, and ſhall be as dead for fear, by reaſon of the expectation which they have of thoſe things which ſhall ſuddenly come upon them: <hi>Luk.</hi> 21. they ſhall lament before the Lord, who ſhall have a flame of fire to do Vengeance and Judgment, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Truth and Juſtice, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe which have not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged God, and who have not obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Goſpel of the Lord, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. and ſhall puniſh them in Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Soul with eternal perdition in the Face of the Lord, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. and in the Glory of his ſtrength. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.2.</p>
                  <p>The bodies of thoſe which are dead before, ſhall come out of the Earth: <hi>Job</hi> 5. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. and of thoſe which ſhall be found living ſhall be changed, and put on immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:153299:74"/>and ſhall be charged with oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brious infamy before God and his Saints: for he ſhall make clear the things that are hid, and ſhall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt the counſels of hearts.</p>
                  <p>And then their immortal Soul ſhall be loaden with fear, with ſorrow, with terrors, with grief, with deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and with ſuch deſpair, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. <hi>Luke</hi> 21. that it is impoſſible for us to comprehend it. <hi>Mar</hi> 13. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p>Then being in ſuch confuſion of Body and Soul, the image of <hi>Satan</hi> their heard ſhall appear upon them: that is to ſay, infidelity, iniquity, wickedneſs, abomination, filthineſs, hatred, cruelty, tyranny, perjury, lying, envy, and all that is of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety and unjuſtice, which is the black Roab of the reprobate: and even ſo as the Elect have Chriſt for their head, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.12. of whom they are the body, unto whom they ſhall be made alike; <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.5. ſo
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:153299:75"/>likewiſe the reprobates have <hi>Belzebub</hi> for theirs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. unto whom they ſhall be made conformable.</p>
                  <p>For although that all the Devils are all Apoſtate Angels, nevertheleſs the Scripture in ſundry places at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes the principality to one alone, to the end to gather all the wicked unto him, as members in one Body, for to be put to perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ruin.</p>
                  <p>Then the wrath and indignation of God ſhall ſhew it ſelf clearly upon all the infidelity and unju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the unbelievers, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. which ſhall not be found written in the book of Life; <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.10.12.25. for which they ſhall receive ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Condemnation, <hi>Mark</hi> 3. and being ſeparated from Chriſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.21. ſhall be driven from before the preſence of the Lord, as the duſt before the wind, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. and caſt like dogs forth
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:153299:75"/>of the City of the Children of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. and ſent with their Captain Satan and his Angles, who did accuſe the elect before God night and day, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 17. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22. in perpetual malediction, for to drink of the wine of the wrath of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. filled in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the cup of his wrath, and ſhall be tormented with fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone before the holy Angels, and before the Lamb, and the ſmoke of their torments ſhall mount for ever, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. 15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16. and they ſhall have no reſt neither day nor night.</p>
                  <p>Now this place of torment for the wicked is ſo horrible, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. that it is incomprehenſible unto us; and even as God is eternal, alſo this ruin ſhall be eternal. The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for to declare it unto us, uſeth many compariſons. <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55. That the wicked ſhall be caſt into the Pit of ruin, and of the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:153299:76"/>bottomleſs Pit. <hi>Rev.</hi> 9. <hi>Iſa.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30. That the torture is already prepared for the wicked, which God hath made deep and large; the Building of it is fire and much wood, and the breath of the Lord like unto a ſtream of Brimſtone doth kindle it; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66. then he ſaith that the worm of the wicked ſhall not die, and therefore ſhall not be quenched, and they ſhall be hateful to all fleſh. <hi>Daniel</hi> ſayeth alſo, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. That they ſhall be in perpetual ſhame and contempt, <hi>Malachy</hi> declares, <hi>Mal.</hi> 4. That the day of the Lord ſhall come burning like an Oven, and all the proud and thoſe that do wickedly ſhall be like ſtubble, and the day of the Lord ſhall burn them, and ſhall leave them neither root nor branch. St. <hi>John Bapiſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. that the chaff ſhall be put into the fire, which ſhall never be quenched, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. The Lord ſaith, that they ſhall be caſt
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:153299:76"/>into the Furnance of Fire, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. which is the everlaſting Fire. Saint <hi>Luke</hi> ſheweth, <hi>Luc.</hi> 16. that the evil rich man whoſe Soul is in Hell, is in ſuch great heat, that he great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſires to have a drop of Water, which he ſhall never be able to get; how much more ſhall he be tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted when he hath put on his body? The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Heb.</hi> s10. that they ſhall feel a ferventneſs of fire, which ſhall devour them. St. <hi>John</hi> declareth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19, 20, 21. That they ſhall be caſt into the lake of fire and brimſtone, which is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond death. For although they ſhall live, yet by reaſon of theſe incredible torments, they ought ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be called dead then alive: Now although that by all theſe ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes it is demonſtrated unto us, that the damned ſhall be grievouſly and everlaſtingly tormented; yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, man cannot think nor comprehend how great the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:153299:77"/>ſufferings ſhall be, no more then he can comprehend the joy of the Children of God, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. Wherefore with good cauſe the Author to the Hebrews ſaith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. that it is a terrible and fearful thing to fall into the bands of the living God. For although that we ſhould ſee one continually knawed with worms, and burnt with fire, that torment ſhould notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be as nothing in regard of that which is prepared for the wicked. For beſides that their bodies ſhall be horribly afflicted, their ſouls ſhall be in incredible diſtreſſes and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows. This ought well to ſtur us up to watch and pray, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frain from doing evil, and to move us to ſerve God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 51. and to deſire him with the Prophets and Apoſtles, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. to change, review and increaſe our faith, that ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made new creatures, we may
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:153299:77"/>eſcape this place of torment, and be numbred amongſt the Sons of God. <hi>Lamen,</hi> 5. <hi>Cant,</hi> 1. <hi>Luc.</hi> 17. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. <hi>Wiſ.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5. Which the Lord grant for the love of his well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Son our Saviour, to whom be all honor and glory for ever and ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayers_and_meditations">
                  <head>Prayers and Meditations touching Life and Death.</head>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>Meditation the Firſt.</head>
                     <p>THe life of Chriſtians ought to be occupied in conſidering the things that follow, and to put them in practiſe; to wit, to have always in remembrance the benefits which they have received at the hands of God; to give him thanks for them without ceaſing, both with heart and mouth; to love him, who is goodneſs it ſelf, to fear and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him, ſeeing he is the Almighty,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:153299:78"/>and only Wiſe; to be ſtirred up by the love which they bear to God, alſo to love their Neighbours. The love of God draws us from the love of corruptible things, lifts us up to Heaven, and inflames our hearts to a holineſs of life. The love of our Neighbour turns us from all trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſomneſs in will or in deed, and doth ſtir us up to integrity, and well doing.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>Another.</head>
                     <p>LEt us often think what we are: The principal part of us is the Soul, the which is endued with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, with reaſon, and with judgment, to know the ſoveraign good, which is God, to love him, to adhere and unite our ſelves unto him, that we may have part of his immortality and happineſs. Now we forſake and contemn this great good, for to grovel upon the earth,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:153299:78"/>and to go down into the pit of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal deſires, applying the vigour of our underſtanding and judgment, to things that are not worth the pains that we employ in them. We bury our ſelves quick, of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly we become earthly, and of men created for eternal life, we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour as much as in us lieth, to ſet our ſelves in the rank of brute Beaſts. God doth not forſake us nevertheleſs, although that our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude hath well deſerved it, but calls us unto him by his word, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents unto us infinite teſtimonies of his grace, continues it daily, he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, exhorts, counſels, chides and fatherly chaſtiſeth us; Nevertheleſs we continue blind, deaf, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent, deſpiſing his goodneſs, or uſe it not as we ſhould, or indeed abuſing it; nay, which is worſe, we love vain and tranſitory things bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and have our minds too much fixed and ſetled upon them. God
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:153299:79"/>ſtretcheth forth his hand to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct us, we draw back ours, and fly when he calleth us. If he put us into the way of ſalvation, we grudge and repine for the world, we look behind us, deferring and remitting our amendment till to morrow. Let us awake then, let us not always ſtick in the mire, let us ſtrengthen our ſelves in the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of him that ſupports and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours us, let us a little undertake to deſpiſe corruptible things, and to deſire thoſe that are truly good and everlaſting. When God calleth us, let us hearken, if he guids us, let us follow him, that we may come to his houſe: let us receive his good things, and himſelf too; for he gives himſelf unto us in the perſon of his Son. He ſhews us the means to get to Heaven, let us then deſire of him to give us the will and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage by faith, repentance, charity and hope to aim thither, and that
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:153299:79"/>he would maintain his grace in us until the end, to ſigh in this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal life, and to wait (through the aſſurance of his mercy) for our depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture out of this world, and our laſt day, which ſhall be the beginning of our true life.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>Prayers and Meditations.</head>
                     <p>HOW great are the illuſions and impoſtures of the enemy of our ſalvation? He ſheweth us afar off things that are ridiculous and vain, and perſwades us that it is all good and happineſs; he ſcares us with things that we ought not to fear; and makes us to fly from thoſe things which we ought to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace. He calleth, inticeth and flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth us, by the means of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires; if that will not ſerve, he roars and ſtorms, and endeavours to aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh us within and without. O eternal Light and Verity, O Lord
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:153299:80"/>and merciful Father, diſperſe thoſe clouds of ignoranee and error, illuminate our underſtanding, and do not ſuffer us to come near to that, which thou haſt commanded us to flie from, and which is hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and pernicious unto us; let us not deſire, but what is truly to be deſired, to wit, thy ſelf, who art the ſpring-head of all goodneſs of our life, and of eternal happineſs. All fleſh is graſs, and the glory of the man is like the flower of the field: cauſe then that we may ſeek for our firmneſs and contentment in the grace which thy Son hath brought us: let our life lye hid in him, ſo that at the day of the ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of our ſouls from our bodies, we may find it holy in Heaven, waiting with aſſured reſt and joy, the happy Reſurrection of this fleſh; in which all corruption, infirmity and ignominy being aboliſhed, and death being ſwallowed up of victory,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:153299:80"/>we ſhall live eternally with thee, in an incomprehenſible happineſs in thee, by the which thou ſhall be glorified. Maintain then thy Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, O Lord, in this faith and hope, finiſhing thy work in us, until they be altogether with thee, for to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the inheritance, and the glory which thine only Son hath by his Merit purchaſed for them, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>Prayer.</head>
                     <p>OLord Jeſus Chriſt, Creator and Redeemer of Mankind, who haſt ſaid, I am the way, the Truth, and the Life, I do beſſech thee by this unſpeakable Charity which thou haſt ſhewed, in yielding thy ſelf to Death for us, that I may never ſtray any jot from the, who art the way; nor that I doubt of thy Promiſes, ſeeing thou art the Truth, and doſt
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:153299:81"/>accompliſh that which thou promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt. Cauſe that I may only take pleaſure in thee, who art the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life, beyond the which there is nothing to be deſired, neither in Heaven nor Earth. Thou haſt taught us the true and only way to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe we ſhould not abide er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring like ſtray'd Sheep in the loſt ways of this World; ſhewing us clearly that which we ought to believe, to do, to hope, and wherein we ought to yield and ſettle our ſelves. It is thou that haſt given us to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, how curſed we are in <hi>Adam;</hi> and that there is no way to eſcape from this Perdition in the which we are plunged, but by Faith in thee. Thou art that true Light which doſt appear to thoſe that walk in the deſert of this Life, and who having drawn us out of the darkneſs of the ſpiritual <hi>Egypt,</hi> haſt driven away the darkneſs of our Underſtanding, and doſt enlighten us, to the end
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:153299:81"/>we may tend towards the promiſed Inheritance, which is the Life Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting; into the which the Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers does not enter, but thoſe that have aſſuredly relied upon thy holy Promiſes. O what a Goodneſs is it that thou haſt vouchſafed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend from thy Fathers-Boſom, and from the Everlaſting Throne to the Earth, to put on our poor Nature; of Maſter to become Servant, to the end that by thy Doctrine thou mighteſt do away the darkneſs of our Ignorance, to guide our feet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the way of Peace, and to make plain the way of Salvation unto us; which if we follow, we cannot ſtray nor wax weary, ſeeing that thy Grace and Power do accompany us therein all the days of our Life.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, by thy Spirit thou doſt ſtrengthen us in it, and double our Courage. Thy word is Bread, which nouriſheth us therein; thy promiſe is the ſtaff which upholds
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:153299:82"/>us. Thou thy ſelf by thy ſecret and incomprehenſible vertue doſt bear and maintain us in it, in an admirable manner; to the end, that both in fair and foul weather, we may walk with all Alacrity unto thee. And as in preſerving us, thou hindereſt that we do not fall into the ſnares of Satan and the World; alſo ſeeing thou art the Truth, thou takeſt away all doubts, ſcruples, and miſtruſts, which may trouble and let us, or turn us during our courſe; thou cauſeſt us to behold the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Vocation, the miſery and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the World, the frailty of this preſent Life, the Gate of Death, and the moſt happy Life which is beyond that. And as thou art this true Life, even in this World thou doſt quicken by thy Truth, us that are poor, wretched, and dead in Sin; thou doſt augment that life by the Miniſtry and Efficacy of thy holy Goſpel, and doſt confirm it
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:153299:82"/>by the uſe of the Sacraments which thou haſt eſtabliſhed to confirm the Faith of thoſe that are thine, until that our Corruption, and what we have in mortality in us, being abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by the Reſurrection, we ſhall be, and live everlaſtingly with thee, both in Body and Soul, when thou ſhalt be all in all. Life Everlaſting is to know the true God, and thee his Son, which wert ſent unto us. Now we ſee thee by Faith in a Glaſs, and in Obſcurity; but one day we ſhall behold thee face to face, and ſhall be transformed into thy Glory, nd wholly reformed unto thy Image. I do beſeech thee, merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Saviour, to increaſe my Faith, that I may be ſo well grounded in the Doctrine of my Salvation, that nothing may turn me from it. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in my Heart the Reverence which I owe thee, that I may never turn from thy Obedience; Strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en me in ſuch ſort, that the allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:153299:83"/>nor threatnings do neither intrap nor aſtoniſh me, but that conſtantly I may cleave unto thee (who art my Life) till Death. Cauſe that in vertue of thy holy Promiſes, and of thy Spirit, I may increaſe more and more in thy Love; and leaving behind me the things of this World, I may tend to that which is firm and perfect. Increaſe thy Grace in me, that every day I may dye in my ſelf, for to be quickned and guided by thy Favour, fearing no other but thou God Almighty, loving nothing but thee, as there is nothing but thee to be beloved; boaſting my ſelf in nothing but in thy only Grace and Mercy, which is the Glory of all thy Servants; ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no other good but thee, nor deſiring any thing but thee, who art the full and entire felicity of all the Faithful, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="163" facs="tcp:153299:83"/>
                     <head>Another.</head>
                     <p>LOrd Jeſus, who art always merciful, who doſt not ſtick to be my Saviour, as well in Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity as in Proſperity. Give me the Grace in all humble obedience to yield unto thy will, when it ſhall pleaſe thee to mingle bitterneſs amongſt ſo many ſweet things which thou cauſeſt me to taſte in living under thy Protection. Thou art admirable and moſt good in the time of Afflictions: In that by ſuch means thou doſt heal ſpiritual Diſeaſes, and in viſiting of us in this World, thou diſpoſeſt us to meditate of a better Life, having thy ſelf ſhewed us the Example thereof. True it is, that I find it very hard to digeſt, but thou haſt been brought to a more ſtrange condition, when for to draw me
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:153299:84"/>out of Hell, thou wenteſt down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it thy ſelf, and for to reconcile me to thy heavenly Father thou haſt undergone his Curſe, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of my Sins. I have ſo often deſerved Hell and the fiery Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and thou deliveredſt me, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring me that I have part in the merits of thy Death, and thy Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and that I am one of thy Co-heirs, for to reign one day with thee in thy Kingdom; and at this preſent in the midſt of ſo many Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, to be nevertheleſs ſet in the heavenly Places. Having part in ſo many good things, why ſhall I vex my ſelf for a little endurance, by the means whereof thou wilt awaken me, and make me better, and draw me ſo much the more to thee? But ſeeing thou knoweſt me better then I know my ſelf, if it be thy pleaſure to put me to any tryal, give me neceſſary force and patience to glorifie thee, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:153299:84"/>all the evil that may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen unto me, to good and Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And if in ſupporting my weakneſs, thy goodneſs is pleaſed to advertiſe me by ſome light affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, cauſe that this thy well-wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling may draw me more and more to love and honour thee, to give thee thanks for the care which thou haſt of thy poor Servant, and by that means to diſpoſe me to weight for thee at my Death, that after it I may find the Life which thou haſt purchaſed for me by thy Death, and therein with thee to have part in Joy and Reſt for Ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="166" facs="tcp:153299:85"/>
                     <head>Another.</head>
                     <p>Lord God Heavenly Father, when I conſider in how many ſorts I have ſinned before thy Face, and againſt thy high Majeſty, I have horrour in my ſelf, in thinking that I have ſo often turned from thee. Propitious and favourable Father, I deteſt my ingratitude; ſeeing in what ſervitude of ſin, I have been too often precipitate, ſelling as much as in my lay of the precious Liberty which thy Son had purchaſed for me. I condemn my folly, I alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether diſlike of my ſelf, I ſee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Death and miſhap hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over my head, and my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience riſing for a Judge and Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my Iniquities. But when on the other ſide I enter into a Contemplation of thy infinite mercy
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:153299:85"/>the which ſurmounteth all thy works, and in the which, if ſo I dare to ſpeak, thou ſurmounteſt thy ſelf, my ſoul is comforted. And indeed, why ſhould I make my ſelf believe that I cannot find grace before him that ſummons and ſo often and gently calls the ſinner to repentance, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting expreſly that he deſires not the death of a ſinner, but rather that he turn from his wickedneſs and live.</p>
                     <p>Moreover thy only Son hath ſo well aſſured us, that we ſhall find favour in thy ſight, by the ſweet words which himſelf had uttered, as that of the loſt ſheep, and of the prodigal Son, the image of whom I acknowledg'd my ſelf to be; that I ſhould be moſt unthankful, incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous and wicked, to go back and to be aſhamed of thy preſence, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I am wretched; ſeeing thou doſt ſo ſtretch forth thy hand unto me, and draw me to thee with ſuch
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:153299:86"/>wonderful affection. I have very vildly forſaken thee; O merciful Father, I have unhappily let ſlip thy Graces; and adhering to deſires of my fleſh, and ſtraying from thy Obedience, I have wrapped my ſelf in the baſe ſervitude of ſin; I am fallen into extream miſery, I know not whether to retire, unleſs it be towards thee whom I have aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned. Let thy mercy receive this poor ſupplication whom thou haſt ſupported during his errors. I am unworthy to lift up mine Eyes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, or to call thee Father; But I pray thee bow down thine Eyes to me, ſeeing thou wilt have it ſo, being without that, in the power of thine Enemies. The ſight of thy Face will revive me, and bring me again to thee. Seeing I have ſome diſpleaſure in my ſelf, I know thou lookeſt upon me, that thou haſt given me Eyes to ſee the danger wherein I was: thou haſt
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:153299:86"/>ſought and found me in death, and in the world, and haſt through thy mercy given me a deſire to enter into thy houſe. I dare not deſire that thou ſhouldſt kiſs and embrace me, nor that hou ſhouldſt weep for joy that thou haſt found thy poor Servant and Slave: I do not demand the precious Ornaments wherewith thou doeſt honour thy great servants and moſt affection<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Children. It is enough for me to be among of the leaſt of thy Houſe, amidſt the greateſt ſinners, that have obtained pardon of thee, and that have ſome ſhelter in thy Palace, where there are ſo many Dwellings: That even in thy Houſe I may be as little as thou ſhalt pleaſe, provided that thou wilt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve me thine for ever.</p>
                     <p>O Merciful Father, I beſeech thee that for the love of thy well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Son my only Saviour, thou wouldſt give me thy holy Spirit,
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:153299:87"/>which may puri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e my heart, and ſtrengthen me in ſuch ſort, that I may always dwell in thy Houſe, there to ſerve thee in Holineſs and Juſtice all the days of my Life. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>Prayers.</head>
                     <p>WHat do we in this world but heap ſins upon ſins? So that the morrow is always worſe then the day before, and we do not ceaſe, drawing thy indignation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us; But being out of this world in thy heritage, we ſhall be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether aſſured of our perfect and eternal felicity, the miſeries of the bodies ſhall be aboliſhed, the vices and filthineſs of the Soul ſhall be done away. O Heavenly Father, increaſe our Faith in us, for fear
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:153299:87"/>leſt we ſhould doubt of things ſo certain; Imprint thy Grace and thy Love in our Hearts, which may lift us up to thee, and ſtrengthen us in thy fear. And becauſe thou haſt lodged us in this World, there for to remain as long as it ſhall pleaſe thee, without declaring unto us the day of our departure, the which thou alone knoweſt. I do beſeech thee to take me out of it when thou in thy mercy pleaſeſt; and then to do me that good that I may acknowledge the ſame, that in the mean while I may fit my ſelf thereuuto, as thou haſt appointed by thy holy Name, through Jeſus Chriſt our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour and Redeemer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="172" facs="tcp:153299:88"/>
                     <head>Another.</head>
                     <p>THis body is the Priſon of the Soul, yea, a dark Priſon, nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and fearful; we are as it were baniſhed men in this world, our life is but woe and miſery: on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, Lord, it is in thy heavenly Kingdom, that we find our Liberty, our Country, and our perfect Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment. A wake our Sould by thy word, to the remembrance and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of ſuch a good; imprint in our Hearts the love and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the Everlaſting good things, and only to be wiſhed for; give un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our Conſciences ſome taſte of that joy wherewith the happy Souls which are in Heaven are filled, that I may hold as dung and filth all that which the Worldlings find ſo fair, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet ſo much, which ſo obſtinately they retain, and do adore with ſuch
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:153299:88"/>fervency. Cauſe that finding taſte but in thy verity and grace, I may wait for (calling upon thee) the day of my perfect deliverance, thro' Jeſus Chriſt thy Son, to whom with thee and the holy Spirit be glory Everlaſting. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>Another.</head>
                     <p>O Lord Jeſus, the only Salvation of the Living, Life everlaſting of the dead, I ſubmit my ſelf to thy holy Will, whether it be thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure yet to ſuffer my Soul to be ſome ſpace within this body, for to ſerve thee, or that it pleaſe thee to take it out of priſon, being aſſured that what thou keepeſt cannot periſh. I am content with all my heart, that my Body return into the Earth, from whence it was taken, believing the
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:153299:89"/>laſt Reſurrection, which ſhall make it immortal, incorruptible, and full of Glory. I do beſeech thee to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie my Sould againſt all temptation, environ me with the buckler of thy Mercy, to beat back the darts of Satan. As for me, I am weakneſs it ſelf, but I rely upon thy ſtrength and goodneſs. I cannot alledge any good thing before thee whereof to boaſt; on the contrary, alas, my ſins, infinite in number, accuſe and torment me, but thy merit aſſures me that I ſhall be ſaved; for I hold for certain, that thou wert born for me, that thou wert tempted, that thou haſt obeyed to God thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that thou haſt taught and brought Life Everlaſting for me; ſeeing thou haſt given thy ſelf to me with all theſe good things, let not ſuch a gift be unprofitable; let thy blood wipe out the filth of my faults, thy Juſtice cover my Iniquities, thy Merits make me to find Grace before
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:153299:89"/>the heavenly Throne. If my Evils do increaſe, augment thy Grace in me; ſo that Faith, Hope, and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity may not dye, but rather wax ſtrong in me: that the apprehenſion of Death do not daunt me, but that even after this body ſhall be as it were dead, cauſe that the Eyes of my Soul may lift themſelves up to Heaven, that the Heart may then cry fervently unto thee, Lord I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my Soul into thy Hands, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil thy work, for thou haſt bought me, I am thine by the Gift of thy Father, to whom with thee and the Holy Ghoſt be Everlaſting Glory, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="176" facs="tcp:153299:90"/>
                     <head>The Humble Suit of a Sinner for the Pardon of his Sins.</head>
                     <p>O Moſt juſt and dreadful God, equitable in all thy Judgments, who ſuffereſt no Sin to paſs unpuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed either in this Life, or in the Life to come. Let me have with <hi>Job</hi> this Conſolation, That afflicting me, thou wouldſt not ſpare me here, to puniſh me hereafter. Here rather burn, here cut, that hereafter thou mayeſt ſpare me. That Union, O God, which thou didſt put at my Creation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt my Soul and my Body, I have not employed for to ſerve thee, therefore I will that henceforth it be diſſolved. For too great affection I had to Riches, and for my ill em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying of them, I will deny my ſelf of all things under the Sun, and will have no more but a Sheet, Coffin, and an hole to lye in, and wait for thy Coming. For the too great love
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:153299:90"/>I carried to my Husband, Wife, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Parents, Friends, Companions, Converſation and Company, I will now willingly abandon them all, and their Embracements and kindly Uſage. I will alſo have an end put to all my Senſes, that henceforth I neither See, Hear, Touch, Taſte nor Smell any thing, for not having ruled them, nor ſhut them up by mortification when the Devil was ſeeking entry into my Soul. From henceforth, Lord, I will put ſilence to this wicked Tongue of mine, which hath been ſo great an Inſtrument of Impiety, ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, lying, curſing, defaming, back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting, detracting, and breaking forth ſo often in impure, diſhoneſt and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious Speeches, againſt thee and my Neighbour.</p>
                     <p>For the too great mind I had to run, go, and walk in the ways of the wicked; For the too frequent, impure poſtures, geſtures, and motions of my Body, I will lye dead in the Grave,
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:153299:91"/>and deſire that henceforth none do ſo much as name me, or ſpeak a word of me, by reaſon I was too deſirous to be in every ones mouth, and to be praiſed and conſerved in their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories; and becauſe I did ſo much affect Honour, Dignity, and the things of the Earth, and did ſo much ſearch after delicate fare, ſoft bedding, and good cloathing, and did nouriſh and pamper this fleſh of mine with too great care; for honour, I will lye in abjection; and for that I aſpired to have others bowing their heads to me, and to be lifted above them, I will have them to trample over me. For my love to the Earth, I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to it; for my Food, I will have the Worms to crawl in and out at my Mouth; for my Bed, I will have a Grave, for my Garments, a Sheet; and for thy dainty uſage of my Body, I will henceforth turn all my Beauty into Corruption. Receive then O juſt God, all theſe things in Puniſhment
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:153299:91"/>of my many Offences, for ſo this being thy juſt Will, it is alſo mine. Only, O god of Juſtice, let my Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment be here in this Life, that I may find thee to be a God of Mercy in the Life to come: (for thou haſt declared by thy Servant <hi>David,</hi> that thy Mercies are above all thy Works.) Grant this O Lord, for the Merits of thy only Son, my Saviour, Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:153299:92" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:153299:92"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:153299:93" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:153299:93" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
